<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions on a book called, A plea for non-scribers. By Ephraim Elcock.</title>
            <author>Elcock, Ephraim.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E636_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865698</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865698</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 98:E636[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions on a book called, A plea for non-scribers. By Ephraim Elcock.</title>
                  <author>Elcock, Ephraim.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Clowes, for Richard Wodnothe, and are to be sold next dore to the Golden-Hart in Leaden-Hall-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 8th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Animadverſions on a Book, CALLED, A PLEA FOR NON-SCRIBERS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb. 14.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They ſaid to one another, Let us make us a Captain, and let us return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Juſtin. Hiſtor. Lib. 38.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Cappadoces munus Libertatis abnuentes, negant vivere gentem ſine REGE poſſe.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Valerius Maxim. Lib. 2. cap. 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Quam impudenter Duronius Roſtra conſcendit illa dicturus, Fraeni ſunt injecti vobis, Quirites, nullo modo perpetiendi: alligati &amp; conſtricti eſtis amaro vinculo ſervitutis: Lex enim lata eſt, quae vos frugi eſſe jubet: abrogemus igitur iſtud horrendae vetuſtatis rubigine obſitum imperium: etenim quid opus Libertate, ſi volentibus luxu perire non licet?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Seneca, Epiſt. 102.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Non debuit hoc nobis eſſe propoſitum, argutias ſerere, &amp; Philoſophiam in has auguſtias de ſua Majeſtate detrahere. Quanto ſatius eſt ire aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ viâ &amp; rectâ, quam ſibi ipſi flexus diſponere, quos cum magnâ mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiâ debeas relegere. Neque enim quicquam aliud iſtae diſputationes ſunt, quam inter ſe peritè captantium luſus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By EPHRAIM ELCOCK.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Clowes,</hi> for <hi>Richard Wodnothe,</hi> and are to be ſold next dore to the <hi>Golden-Hart</hi> in <hi>Leaden-Hall-ſtreet,</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117947:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117947:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Councel of <hi>State,</hi> appointed by the Authority of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Bavaria</hi> (the fifth <hi>German</hi> Emperor of that name) was ſore baited by Pope <hi>John</hi> the <hi>22.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Defende me (O Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar) ab inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis Papae en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe tuo, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go te verbo, ſcripto, rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubilibus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus eum tuebor. Phil. Mornay. du Pleſſis. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. p. 451. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.9. Anatomy of Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Preface to the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. p. 7.</note> 
               <hi>William Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kam</hi> (our Countrey-man) who merited the name of <hi>Dr. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutiſſimus,</hi> ſaid to him, defend me <hi>(O Caeſar)</hi> from the injuries of the <hi>Pope,</hi> by your Sword, and I will defend you by word, writing, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable Arguments againſt him. I dare not challenge ſuch acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or efficacy of arguing to my poor Labours here preſented to your Honours; and therefore rather humbly crave your Protection of them and their Authour, then dare to think my ſelf your Protector.</p>
            <p>Your Honours are under a higher Guard, even his, who is a Sun and Shield to the upright, and to whom the Shields of the Earth (the <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi>) do belong.</p>
            <p>Of the Book I may ſay, as our <hi>Democritus,</hi> out of <hi>Macrobius,</hi> of his own works, <hi>Omne meum nihil meum:</hi> the Collection was mine, the matter other mens; and indeed, it is more then an Echo, an imperfect repetition of more perfect voices.</p>
            <p>Yet it is what I have, and ſince it concernes the late tranſactions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> your <hi>Motion</hi> in a high Orbe therein, moved me to deſire your gracious aſpect, and your ſweet influences upon our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> incourage me to hope acceptation.</p>
            <p>Diverſions from the common road are uſually look't upon as Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes; though reaſon and our Law allow a Commander in purſuit of publick enemies to march his men through any mans encloſure. So He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical actions of vertue againſt Tyrants, and their complices, are ſcil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with unworthy aſperſions, by them who adore a form, though cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and prefer private tranquillity before publick ſafety, though God and nature dictate. That meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which might at firſt have been
<pb facs="tcp:117947:3"/> choſen or refuſed, are no longer to be uſed then while they are ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to their proper ends; and when they oppoſe them, are abſolutely to be rejected; leſt what was meant for Medicine turn to poyſon.</p>
            <p>A great part of the filth caſt upon the late actions, is directed againſt your Honours in ſpecial, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our victorious Army: But, as God hath born <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itneſs to their integrity, by giving victory over the adverſaries after ſolemn appeales to his deciſion: ſo your Honours have hitherto ſo managed your truſt, and bin ſo ſignally ſaved by the Lord, the ſhield of your help,<note place="margin">Deut. 33.29</note> and the ſword of your Excellency, that all your enemies have been found Lyars.</p>
            <p>Go on <hi>(Right Honourable)</hi> to do worthily in and for our Land, and the good Lord ſuggeſt to you more and more efficacious meanes for the advancement of his glory, and the welfare of our Nation, ſupport you with courage and vigour, that your Councels may be brought to the wiſhed effect; That <hi>England</hi> which hath been look't upon as a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion forſaken of her God, may (by the good hand of God u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on your care and wiſdom) be made a praiſe in the ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, and ſet up in perfect beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and that your memorial in after ages may be, Theſe are the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairers of the breach, the reſtorers of pathes to dwell in; which is the humble prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(Right Honourable)</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant. EPHRAIM ELCOCK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117947:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader, whoever thou be,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Will not foretel thy judgement, I could like that Writers might be bound to the ſame conditions,<note place="margin">Ubbo Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius de Rep. Ath. p. 35.</note> that they were who pleaded before the <hi>Areopagites, viz.</hi> that they ſhould plead, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, neither uſe exordiums to flatter into a good opinion, nor perorations to move pitty; yet I am neceſſitated to advertiſe thee of a few things.</p>
            <p>It may be thought that this Treatiſe is born out of due time, becauſe it took not hold of the heel of what it oppoſeth. But I beſeech thee know,<note place="margin">Ad haec faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le procuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da magis i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem poſſis, quàm <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrum Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium</hi> civem tuum, lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſum, tum (quod ego in hac re pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum puto) neutiquam in amici ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotio dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitantem. Ang. Polit. Epiſt. Dedic. ante Herod. latinitate donatum. Tit. 1.13. <hi>P. Servita.</hi> Hiſtory of the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. pag. 61. 62.</note> 
               <hi>1.</hi> That the report of the <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> Plea came to my eares, long before the Book it ſelf came to my hands. <hi>2.</hi> That I long waited for ſome of better abilities to undertake it. <hi>3.</hi> That it was neither my only, nor greateſt buſineſs, when undertaken, and therefore went on ſlowly, as being compoſed at houres ſpared from other and higher employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>4.</hi> That when it was perfected, I was timerous of its publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being conſcious of my own weakneſs, and this being the firſt parox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme of writing for the publick view that ever I was taken with. <hi>5.</hi> That when it was brought to the birth, it lay long in danger of dying there, for want of a Man Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wife, I mean ſuch a friend as <hi>Alexander Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> was to <hi>Angelus Politianus</hi> in the publication of his tranſlation of <hi>Herodian,</hi> till providence found me out ſuch a o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; to whom as I am ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recompenſably engaged, ſo thou alſo art obliged for any good that thou receiveſt hence.</p>
            <p>Some things may ſeem to thee too harſh; but conſider, <hi>1.</hi> The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of mens tempers, requireth diverſity of remedies. Some muſt be ſharply reproved, that they may be ſound. <hi>2.</hi> The nature of the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; he ſpoke reaſon that ſaid, Humane Majeſty is not offended, but with a certain malice and deſire of him that offendeth, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie very often is through ignorance; whence this for the moſt part de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves compaſſion, that never. <hi>3.</hi> Some men muſt be anſwered in their own way. It's a hard thing for him that deales with <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract ſome-what of their petulancy, ſaith the Prefacer to <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Conclave. Look upon the height of the adverſe writing, and thou wilt confeſs that againſt ſuch a peece
<q>Difficile eſt Satyram non Scribere.—</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou be candid and ingenuous, I need not beg thy pardon for common frailties: if thou be not, I ſhall but loſe my labour in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:117947:4"/>
            <head>To the worthy Authour of theſe <hi>Animadverſions.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe reiterated thanks wherein you have expreſſed a great ſenſe of the ſmall pains, which I freely took, to make your <hi>Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> publick; doth oblige me to apologize for the long delay of this publication; for I think it juſt that the publick ſhould know that your part of this work was long agoe performed: Seeing it is at leſt (if I miſtake not) <hi>9.</hi> or <hi>10.</hi> Moneths ſince; I ſaw the Manuſcript where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you were delivered of this birth: but the want of fit addreſſes (you being unacquainted with the way) to appear in publick, hath almoſt ſtifled this Infant, ſince it had life: at leſt it comes now into the world almoſt out of due time.</p>
            <p>For my own part, I had without your knowledge accidentally the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal thereof; and although I found (as then I told the party who ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it unto me) ſomething more ſharp in it then my <hi>Genius</hi> did affect; yet finding it alſo a piece both judicious, accurate and ſolid as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and alſo full of learning, of good reading, and of quickneſs of ſpirit, as to your manner of handling that matter, I thought my ſelf bound in love to the truth, and to the publick good, to lend it the hand of a Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife, in bringing it to the Preſſe; which could be done but very ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, partly becauſe of the lets which the <hi>Stationers</hi> and <hi>Printers,</hi> to whom application was made, did caſt us; partly becauſe of other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which took me off from minding this deſign; wherein the publick cauſe, is much beholden to you, and ſuch as are ingenuous, will no leſſe acknowledge it, then doth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Friend and Servant in Chriſt, J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 13. line 10. for <hi>Joſua</hi> read <hi>Hoſea,</hi> p. 31. l. 21. for <hi>is</hi> r. <hi>as,</hi> p. 34. l. 28. for <hi>tooting</hi> r. <hi>footing,</hi> p. 39. l. 2. for <hi>Tithes</hi> r. <hi>Titles,</hi> l. 27. for <hi>either</hi> r. <hi>neither,</hi> l. 28. for <hi>or</hi> r. <hi>nor:</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117947:4"/>
            <head>A Preface in anſwer to <hi>Non-ſcribers Apology.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a good obſervation of <hi>Seneca's</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtile of <hi>Macenas</hi> a great ſtickler for <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his tyranny,<note place="margin">Haec verba tam imprebè ſtructa, tam contra con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinem omnium po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita, oſtendunt mores quoque non minus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vos &amp; pravos &amp; ſingulares fuiſſe. Sen. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>114.</hi>
               </note> That the ill ſtructure and uncouth compoſure of his words, argued his manners to be naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſingular. The ſame obſervation may be made upon the many battologies of theſe Advocates for Tyranny: but their faſtidious vanity is eſpecially viſible in the Title of their Book, they call Non-ſcribers, which laſt word was never before this attempt of theirs naturalized <hi>Engliſh:</hi> a word it is of as abſurd derivation, as that <hi>Anticomarita;</hi> concerning which, <hi>Eraſmus</hi> was fain to bring in a Synod of <hi>Grammarians,</hi> to know whence it came, and what it meant; whereof one ſaid it was an Herbe, another a Fiſh, a third a woman, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſm. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loqu. Synod. Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum.</note> The elegancy of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r etymologie, together with the perplexedneſs of the Syntax will require a Synod of themſelves to reſolve us. Non-ſcribers, (take it in the beſt ſence) are thoſe that write not, and had they meant themſelves, it had been fitter to have called their Book, the plea of Non-ſcribers, then for Non-ſcribers: ſo that it may be thought, that they intended it for a plea for them that were illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate, and could not write for themſelves. The next thing in the front of your Book is their pretence to modeſty; to the vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of which vertue to themſelves, they make an Eſſay in theſe words, — what we ſhall ſay may like the words of wiſe men,<note place="margin">Plea. &amp;c. Pag. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> (though we boaſt not to be ſuch) be heard in ſecret. Yet as if they had forgotten what their Title promiſeth, load the opinion they are about to impugne, and the perſons with whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, with many condemnatory invectives;<note place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> before they produce one Argument, calling engaging ſin; Engagers, ſuch as are going
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117947:5"/> on in their ſin; and the Engagement, the <hi>Helena</hi> of the <hi>Northern</hi> Subſcribers. What modeſty it is to condemn an action, opinion, or perſon for ſinful, before proving them ſuch, I care not to let the moſt impudent judge. It hath been ever held to be modeſty for a man that entereth into controverſie, to think humbly of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, at leaſt-wiſe not to be his own Trumpeter; yet theſe men that before diſclaimed boaſting of their wiſdom,<note place="margin">Plea. &amp;c. pag. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> tell us, that they are the peaceable of the Land, the very words of her whom the Scripture calls a wiſe woman, and point us to the place, leaſt the Reader ſhould doubt of their wiſdom.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.16.19.</note> And in another place they intimate, that had we wanted this product of a <hi>Parturient</hi> Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Preſſe had been no leſſe injurious to poſterity, then the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Midwives had been,<note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. pag. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> had they obey'd <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> Edict, for ſtrangling the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> males; as if what they writ only had <hi>maſculine</hi> ſtrength, and the fruits of all others were but <hi>faemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> productions of the Scriptures, which Garniſh their frontis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, the firſt returns in their book, the ſecond makes nothing for them, ſince no <hi>Agrippa</hi> gave them leave to ſpeak; and there is much difference between licenſed publick ſpeaking to the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of a Judge, and unlicenſed pamphleting to the ſtirring up of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. pag. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>Yet this their way (after ſome few intimations of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation to that purpoſe) they defend as lawful by four rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is a weighty caſe of Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe concerning many, and among others themſelves, and thoſe in relation to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe difficult to reſolve. To this we anſwer, that if weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty caſes of Conſcience, becauſe concerning many, and difficult of reſolution, oblige Miniſters to give a publick teſtimony of their opinions, it obliges them in all ſuch things: and by this ſhift it will not be lawful for the Magiſtrate to make any new Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Miniſters have caſt in their verdict: at leaſtwiſe, none is to obey before they have declared. If nothing of a religious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction muſt be ordained by the Magiſtrate, but what is approved by theſe <hi>Cenſors,</hi> what is the Magiſtrate but the meer <hi>Lictor</hi> of the Miniſters?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. pag. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>2. Becauſe the Engagement is not left voluntary, but ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under a penalty, and they ought to ſpeak before they be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117947:5"/> To which we ſay, 1. That this liberty of ſpeech is their due, when they are particularly accuſed, or have perſonal actions before a Judge, not where they are ſuffered to be at quiet. 2. That it is a liberty of ſpeech particularly to be uſed to the Magiſtrates, before whom they are convented, face to face, and not to be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by ſtealth among the people. 3. That it is a liberty to anſwer concerning the crimes that are laid to their charge, which is to be allowed, but not to queſtion the Authority of the Magiſtrate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom they are convented.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 7.32.49.50.</note> Theſe things concur in them whom Non-ſubſcribers pretend to be their examples. Chriſt's per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was aimed to be taken, the High-Prieſts pronounced his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers accurſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.63, 64.</note> 
               <hi>Nicodemus</hi> pleads that he might face to face anſwer the crimes that he was charged with. Chriſt when called before the High-Prieſts, queſtioned not their power, but anſwered to their queſtions, concerning that which they thought his crime.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe they have no other way to plead their cauſe. Yes, 1.<note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. page <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Before them that tender the Engagement, when they are perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called to it. 2. Before the Judges, in caſe they have any action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, wherein the refuſal of their Engagement is pleaded: and I doubt not, but if they modeſtly propoſe their doubts, the Judges and Juſtices will to their power endeavour to ſatisfie them. Beſides, ſuppoſe there be no other way to plead their cauſe, yet this ſhould have been avoided, becauſe not a ſuitable meanes to accompliſh their end, this being like rather to exaſperate the Magiſtrate againſt them. They either miſtake, or elſe ſpeak ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, when they ſay, that all their pleas are ſhut up, upon pleading of their denial of the Engagement: there is no denial (for ought I know) of their liberty of pleading, that they are not ſatisfied in it, and the Judges have (as I hear) particular inſtructions in their charges to clear its Juſtice.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe they that write for it publiſh their Reaſons.<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> By this Argument <hi>Campian</hi> might have argued it lawful to have written invectives againſt the right of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> becauſe many did defend it. In thoſe things wherein difference in opinion cannot hurt the publick welfare, it is but juſt that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of both ſides ſhould have liberty to print;<note place="margin">Paul Servita Hiſtory of the inquiſition, page <hi>76.</hi>
               </note> but in the things that concern the publick peace, the Magiſtrate hath reaſon to encourage them that endeavour to promote it, and to diſcourage them who would endanger it. Upon this ground the King of <hi>Spain</hi> forbad the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117947:6"/> publiſhing of the 11. Tome of <hi>Baronius</hi> his Annals in his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe it tended to the weakening of the <hi>Sicilians</hi> fidelity, and he is for this commended by one zealous enough for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the <hi>Eccleſiasticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence they proceed to apologize for themſelves, wherein they endeavour to clear themſelves from four ſorts of imputations laid upon them.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15.</note> The firſt of which is their being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> buſie bodies in other mens matters, in matters of the State. From which charge they hope to eſcape,<note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. pag. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> by telling us, that they deal not as <hi>States-men;</hi> but are not to be confined, if States-mens Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs come under <hi>Evangelical</hi> Doctrines. This diſtinction they learnt (it may be) from <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Speed in Hen.</hi> 2. S. 30. <hi>p.</hi> 492.</note> who would not ſubſcribe the Charters confirmed by Parliament; but with this clauſe, <hi>ſalvo honere Dei,</hi> upon which King <hi>Henry</hi> rightly deſcanted, when he told the King of <hi>France,</hi> that whatſoever diſliked <hi>Becket,</hi> he would ſay that it was againſt Gods honour. Some moderate men among the Papiſts ſay, that the Pope hath no power in temporals, in <hi>ordine ad ſpiritualia:</hi> and yet this power hath been ſo exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,<note place="margin">Paul Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, Hiſtory of the inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. p. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> that (as an Authour of their own ſaith) when a Potentate hath not the favour of him that commands in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Religion is made a pretext to oppreſs him. So that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting but <hi>ecce duo gladii,</hi> with the <hi>Canoniſts</hi> interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſet theſe men in the ſeat of him that exalts himſelf above all that is called God, notwithſtanding their ſhifting diſtinction. 2. They cannot be able to reſolve mixt controverſies concerning State buſineſs,<note place="margin">Soveraign Power of Parliaments, part. <hi>3.</hi> page <hi>134.</hi>
               </note> of a religious reduction (as themſelves love to ſpeak) except they deal as Stateſmen. Mr. <hi>Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> (who is their fellow-helper in this cauſe) told their brother <hi>Ferne</hi> heretofore out of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquius, Theologorum utcunque diſertiſſimorum ſententiae in hac controverſia non ſunt multum faciendae, quia quid lex humana ſit ipſi ignorant.</hi> 3. Our Saviour Chriſt, who affirms his Kingdom not to be of this world, would nor be a Judge between Brethren in dividing inheritances;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 18.36. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.14.</note> much leſſe can we ſuppoſe that he hath left a power to his Churches Officers, <hi>quâ tales,</hi> to decide of rights to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power in Commonwealths, or can they produce any Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Rules,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 8.13.</note> and Evangelical Doctrines to that purpoſe. 4. Their inſtance of <hi>Amos</hi> his preaching againſt <hi>Bethel,</hi> was ſure written when they were half aſleep, the Argument was thus. It's no being buſie-bodies, for the <hi>Cheſhire</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Miniſters to do as <hi>Amos</hi> did; but he prophecied againſt Idolatrous <hi>Bethel,</hi> though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117947:6"/> it were the Kings Court, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the <hi>Cheſhire</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, are not buſie-bodies, if they determine of Tithes in the State; an Argument <hi>à Baculo ad Angulum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next imputation that they endeavour to clear themſelves from, is a proſecuting of ſome ſelf-intereſt:<note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. page <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> to which end (after ſome good words and Proteſtations of your innocency) they tell us, That if they ſtood upon any ſuch deſigns, they might obtain thoſe ends by compliance, for they are not ſo ſtupid as not to know which way the ſtream was. The 12. Biſhops that declared the Parliaments actions null without their preſence, ſaw (no doubt) as well as Non-ſcribers, which way the ſtream run, and how probable it was that their tyranny was at a period: They (no doubt) had many intereſts that would have perſwaded them to ſilence, yet for all this they run themſelves into a <hi>Praemunire.</hi> A man may have many luſts and intereſts, whereof one may keep down another. He that is covetous enough may ſometime be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, and ſeem careleſs of his riches, being overprized by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſway of ambition. So that notwithſtanding their profeſſions and this ſhadow of reaſon, they muſt ſeek better Arguments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can excuſe themſelves from being the Prophets of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab's</hi> Son, (for he that was the <hi>Ahab</hi> of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>page</hi> 37.</note> hath now ſhed his blood, where he began to ſhed the blood of <hi>Naboth) Micajah</hi> is neither their Patron or Pattern,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.11.</note> they are liker the Iron-horned <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> who cry throughout all their book, to that bloody and Idolatrous houſe, Go up and proſper.</p>
            <p>The third charge they anſwer to is apoſtacy and malignancy.<note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. page <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> In anſwer to which they tell us, That they have committed nothing againſt the cuſtom of their Fathers. So the Phariſees were earneſt for the tradition of their Fathers: they know,<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> 
               <hi>conſtuetudo ſine ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, vetuſtas erroris eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>But thoſe good Fathers, whence they ſay they're born,<note place="margin">At non ille ſatum quo te mentiris A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles talis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat— Virgil.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The Commons never, ſo as they, did ſcorne.</l>
            </q>
            <p>If they mean Mr. <hi>Knox,</hi> Learned <hi>Buchanan,</hi> Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> it will be ſhewed them that they walk not in their wayes: but if they mean Father <hi>Maxwel</hi> with his <hi>ſacro-ſancta Regum Majeſtas</hi> and Arch-Deacon <hi>Ferne,</hi> we will confeſs what they ſay to be very true. They tell us, that they ſeek and practiſe what they can, that the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117947:7"/> people of the Land may live a quiet and a peaceable life in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and honeſty;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.2.</note> but not a word of praying for them in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which the Apoſtle points as a <hi>medium</hi> to thoſe ends. They would perſwade us of their innocency in the things that are laid to their charge, by theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe they are hated by Malignants, Incendiaries, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And we believe them: It's natural to ſuch to hate the Traytor, though they love the Treaſon. Beſides, ſuch have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful hearts, and let them ſtroke them never ſo much, will (if ever they get power) remember their former oppoſitions; their preſent compliance with them will not ſave them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plea &amp;c. page</hi> 8. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2, 28</note>2. They appeal to their former actions; A weak Argument: <hi>Joab</hi> turned after <hi>Adonijah,</hi> though he turned not after <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To the continued tenour of them and their conſtant walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: ſome that know theſe Miniſters think otherwiſe of their conſtancy then they do themſelves. Sure I am, a great part of them were ſo conſtant to their firſt principles, that they neither prayed for Divine aſſiſtance againſt <hi>Hamilton</hi> and his Army, nor gave thanks for deliverance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them.<note place="margin">Atteſtation of the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. p. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> Tales may be told how ſome pleaded for the expunging of a paſſage againſt that Army, which is in the <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Miniſters Atteſtation. And another anſwered one that askt why he omitted thanks for that deliverance, that he knew not whether it were a mercy or no: yet the Kirk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> declared againſt them. If this be conſtancy, what is liberty? Beſides,<note place="margin">Ameſ. de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſib: Conſcien. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> will tell them, that to Chriſtian conſtancy is required, not only a perpetual continuation of the ſame purpoſe and diſpoſition, and a frequent reiteration of the ſame Acts: but progreſs and proficiency alſo in the way of vertue. The Heathens are taxed as relapſers, becauſe they withheld the truth in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.22.24.</note> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> as forſakers of God, becauſe they followed him not fully. So there is a ſort of men, who in the beginning of civil Wars againſt Tyrants, are hot and active; but through ſloath and unconſtancy,<note place="margin">Tenure of Kings and Magiſtrates. page <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and weakneſs of ſpirit, either fainting ere their own pretences, though never ſo juſt, be half attained, or through an inbred falſeneſs and wickedneſs, betray of-times to deſtruction men of Nobleſt temper, joyned with them for cauſes, which they in their raſh undertakings were not capable of: and that theſe men are ſuch, they themſelves may ſee, if they would view their faces
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117947:7"/> in the Glaſſe held up to them by this worthy Authour,<note place="margin">Nos interea Patrem lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, nè excae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari patiatur cor Anglicani Regis, qui certè diſcere debebit, quanta in iis quae pollicer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poteſtis, fides adhibenda ſic Catholicis ſubditis, quia nè ſe perjurio alligent, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt ſpiritum emittere quam vocem. Introduction to the Arch Biſhops Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. page <hi>82.</hi>
               </note> to anſwer whoſe Reaſons I muſt refer them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They urge their preſent ſtanding out againſt the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as an Argument of their conſtancy to their firſt principles. A ſtrange confidence, hardly to be paralleld, unleſs it be in that paſſage of the <hi>Popes</hi> Bull to the Catholiques of <hi>England,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them from the Oath of Allegiance. We in the mean time will pray the Father of lights, that he will not ſuffer the heart of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> King to be blinded, who certainly ought to learn, how great credit is to be given to his Catholique Subjects, in the things which you can promiſe, who rather would loſe their lives, then let go a word that might oblige them to perjury.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They tell us that they are not changed, but the thing called Malignity: If this were ſo, others have done but as <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> themſelves, what they formerly called Tyranny, they now call fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Government. But Malignity is ſtill the ſame as it was, <hi>viz.</hi> diſaffection to the Common-wealth and enmity againſt liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, they ſay, the Malignants take the Engagement. So they did the Covenant, yet it never the worſe, no though <hi>Hamilton; Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, Inchiqueen, Langdale</hi> ſaid, they fought for it. A returning enemy is much better then a revolting Brother.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, they ſay they are charged with moroſity, wilfulneſs, diſcontent, and prepoſſeſſion; from which they would vindicate themſelves by urging their many near and dear concernments ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon them, which they will not be thought ſo careleſs of,<note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. p. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> as not to regard, if conſcience would permit. They know that <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> had many engagements upon him by divers concernments,<note place="margin">Exodus at the beginning</note> which might have cauſed him to let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go: yet his wilfulneſs was ſuch, as to run him into the deſtruction of his people, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and ſelf alſo at the laſt. Impotent wilfulneſs makes a man forget all ſelf-intereſt. The late King from whom they borrowed this Argument (as indeed this Book of theirs makes that Image of the Beaſt (ſo a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Proverbs</hi> 28.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.32. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Med.</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 2.</note> King, and the King of Kings all Tyrants) to live and give it power to ſpeak, and threatens with death them that will not receive it) he in his book ſaith, My own and my Childrens Intereſts gave me many obligations to ſeek and preſerve the love and welfare of my Subjects: yet theſe Intereſts could not keep him from waging a bloody Warre againſt his people to ſatisfie his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117947:8"/> exorbitant wilfulneſs.<note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. p. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> They ſay it is pure conſcience that is their motive: we wiſh it were ſo, and believe it is ſo in ſome that are led by them, and much pitty the credulity of ſuch: but what Conſcience the leaders among them have (for there are ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Miniſters that pin their faith upon other mens ſleeves) ſhall be ſhewed hereafter in examining their grounds to which they appeal. You would little think that theſe men that thus plead for Conſcience,<note place="margin">Petition of <hi>12500.</hi> &amp;c. page <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> were the promoters of a Petition againſt all ſeparate Congregations, and deſired that no Members of ſuch might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to any place of publick truſt. Yet inſtead of ſeeing in this their affliction, which in their delivered Conſciences, (if they be conſcientious) will not ſuffer them to do what is lawful, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging with <hi>Adonibezek</hi> that God is righteous, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely perſecute others by cenſuring their Conſciences, nay and plainly ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judges</hi> 1.7.</note> that they are angry with them, becauſe they have not ſo great a ſwallow as themſelves. Of theſe we may ſay as the holy Chronicler of <hi>Ahaz.</hi> Theſe are the Miniſters, who when they were afflicted,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chronicles</hi> 28.22. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.25. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.11. <hi>compared.</hi>
               </note> did yet more wickedly. Had their Apology been modeſt, I ſhould not have troubled the Reader with thus much; but ſince they deal in proud wrath, <hi>Solomon,</hi> as he tells them their name, ſo he directs us how to deal with them, that the ſimple may be wiſe, and beware.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters in their <hi>Appendix</hi> anſwer ſome Arguments which are made by others for the Engagement. I ſhall not ſtand upon their Anſwer to any Argument, that I make not uſe of my ſelf: But leave the <hi>Northern</hi> Subſcribers, and the Authour of the grand caſe of Conſcience to ſpeak for themſelves; for they have both age and abilities; which I may more truly ſay of them, then theſe men of their <hi>Baal Berith:</hi> which terme I deſire that it may not be underſtood as if I derogated from the Covenant, but as ſetting forth the abuſe of it by theſe men, who make it a perfect and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat directory for all things ſacred and civil. It cannot be a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to it to be called ſo, in reſpect of the abuſe, no more then it was to the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> to be called <hi>Nehuſhtan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.4.</note> when it was I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolized.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117947:8"/>
            <head>Animadverſions on a Book, called a Plea for <hi>Non-ſcribers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT alwayes hath been the practice of men that delight in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitigation to obſcure things in themſelves plain, by their deviſing of many ſences for them. This do the Non-ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers (for I ſhall hereafter uſe this name which themſelves have impoſed on themſelves) charging the Engagement with a <hi>Protean</hi> ambiguity; from which diverſity of interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they require ſome to free them,<note place="margin">Spumantem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que dari (pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cora inter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertia) votis Optat A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prum, aut fulvum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendere monte Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Virgil. Aenead. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> whoſe interpretation may bear a warrant in it. A deſire fit for Non-ſcribers modeſty, who as youthful <hi>Aſcanius</hi> weary of chaſing fearful <hi>Deere,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Wiſhed a foaming Boare (his Game to mend)</l>
                  <l>Or-Lion from the Mountain to deſcend.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So they dare Authority: all other reaſon is but <hi>impar congreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Achilli.</hi> Yet to let them ſee that the Engagement is not of ſuch a <hi>Protean</hi> ambiguity; but that an engager may agree with them in that ſence, which they ſay is moſt plain, proper and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, I ſhall (after rectifying a few miſtakes of theirs) cloſe with them in the main of their conſtruction.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Plea. &amp;c. Pag. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> By the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> they underſtand a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular form of Government: But here is the matter with its form, the people or community of <hi>England,</hi> in the form of a Common-wealth: as the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> was the people of <hi>England</hi> under that form of Monarchy. This they might have diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erned in the Acts they quote themſelves,<note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. pag. <hi>10.</hi> in the Margin.</note> where they find men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Nation under this preſent Government, and the well
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117947:9"/> Government thereof in a way of Common-wealth or free State: ſo that when it is ſaid the Common-wealth of <hi>England, England</hi> is not<note n="*" place="margin">As they ſay, Appendix. p. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> a whole abſtracted from all formes, but cloathed with its form of a Common-wealth or free State.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Ariſt. polit. l. <hi>6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>2. They underſtand that this is inveſted in certain perſons: but this betrayes their ignorance in the nature of a Common-wealth, or free State: it being proper to a Common-wealth, that in <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudes,</hi> the ſame perſons both command &amp; obey: And therefore, when we engage to a Common-wealth, we underſtand the viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Magiſtrates: we engage to this Parliament for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and to all other Repreſentatives of the people hereafter to be choſen; and to the people we engage to preſerve their liberty of chuſing their Repreſentatives. For, a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Common-wealth is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Government in which the people Govern,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Polit. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> which they could not be made to do, had they not the liberty to elect their ſupreme Magiſtrates. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe miſtakes many of their Arguments are grounded; and hence it followes, that in many things they fight againſt a man of ſtraw,<note place="margin">Quae enim populi partes in civitate, ſi jure ſuffragii in creandis Magiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis ſimilibus deſtituatur? Vbbo Emmius Deſcript. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipub. Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis pag. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> that themſelves have ſet up.</p>
            <p>In the matter and form of the Engagement, I agree with them, and confeſs it is not in the power of the Engagers, as ſingle private perſons, to put a period to its duration; but in the hands of the engaged to, <hi>viz.</hi> the people of <hi>England,</hi> in the form of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. It lies I ſay, in their power to chuſe to themſelves what other form ſhall hereafter moſt tend to their own being and wel-being, which is the end of all civil ſociety. The whole ſenſe of the Engagement is this, <hi>I declare and promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that I will be true and faithful, not only negatively, but poſitively, to the people of England, as now moulded in the form of a Common wealth, with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t a King or Houſe of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us hear their Plea againſt it. In the firſt place they argue thus. A power unjuſt in attainment and poſſeſſion, we cannot be either poſitively or negatively fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful to:<note place="margin">Plea &amp;c. pag. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> But, the power in the Engagement is ſuch: <hi>Ergo</hi> Neither of theſe prppoſitions are unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably true; the weakneſs of the Major and its ſupporters hath been ſufficiently evinced, by a moſt able and learned Authour, in anſwer to the exercitation concerning uſurped Powers. I purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbear to anſwer it (not out of doubt of its infirmity, but) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſpecious pretences that ſuch as Non-ſcribers take,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117947:9"/> from defenſe of the lawfulneſs of ſubmiſſion and obedience to Powers unjuſt in attainment, to beſpatter the preſent power,<note place="margin">See Plea &amp;c. pag. <hi>34.</hi> Plea &amp;c. pag. <hi>19.20.</hi> Appendix. page <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as confeſſed to be unjuſt by its defenders. Of which fault, of wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuppoſitions into conceſſions, the Non-ſcribers are not inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
            <p>Come we then to the examination of the Minors ſtrength: for the confirming of which they argue from two <hi>mediums.</hi> The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent power (ſay they) is unjuſt in its attainment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of its removal, diſpoſition, and ſubverſion of the ancient eſtabliſhed Government, which was a multiformed or compound Magiſtracy of King, Lords, and Commons, coordinate the one to the other. I expected in a charge of this nature, that they ſhould have brought another ſort of Argument, and have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, That it was unlawful for a free people, upon any grounds whatſoever, to have changed their forms of Magiſtracy. This ſeems to be their opinion,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſtandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g in the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but the community is in the power and dignity above the Magiſtrates. Numb. <hi>11.16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hos Judices in magnis mortibus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſitas crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Dici Dictatores poterant. Flavius <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> vocavit, quod nomen etiam Syllae, Cynnae, Marióque &amp; aliis Dictatoribus Romanis Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci dedêre. Petrus Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aeus de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. Hebrae. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> which they expreſs in theſe words. For a privative or innovative power to be in them (that is in the people)<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſtandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g in the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but the community is in the power and dignity above the Magiſtrates. Numb. <hi>11.16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hos Judices in magnis mortibus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſitas crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Dici Dictatores poterant. Flavius <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> vocavit, quod nomen etiam Syllae, Cynnae, Marióque &amp; aliis Dictatoribus Romanis Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci dedêre. Petrus Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aeus de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. Hebrae. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> when they ſtand in the relation of Subjects, that is, have an actual and legitimate ſupreme Magiſtracy over them, we cannot yet ſee any warrant for. I ſhall help them therefore to ſome ſpectacles, through which they may diſcern this truth, That the Community may change their form of Magiſtrary upon which the whole controverſie depends. The people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> before they had Kings, were under an actual and legitimate Magiſtracy, <hi>viz.</hi> The Councel of 70. Elders, inſtituted by divine Authority, they were governed in a way of Policy or free State, by theſe their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives, choſen from among the people. The Judges were an extraordinary kind of Officers, raiſed up by God upon emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occaſions, otherwiſe in the intervalls of Judges <hi>Iſrael</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad no Magiſtracy. Now for this aſſertion, learned <hi>Cunaeus</hi> is evident Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity created theſe Judges in great concluſions of State. And he ſaith further, They may be called Dictators, (and mean <hi>Hiſtorians:</hi> know that the Dictators power was extraordinary) but <hi>Joſephus</hi> calls them Monarchs, which name the <hi>Greeks</hi> gave to <hi>Sylla, Cinna, Marius,</hi> and other <hi>Roman</hi> Dictators. The ſame Authour ſhewes that the Councel of 70. remained ever in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Common-wealth, from its firſt inſtitution, and handled thoſe things that were <hi>ſummae poteſtatis,</hi> of the ſupreme Authority. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> is a clear witneſs too. God ordained (ſaith he) among the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117947:10"/> an Ariſtocracy near a free State,<note place="margin">Ariſtocrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Politiae vicinam [Deus] apud Iſraelitas inſtituit, cum optimâ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione res habere vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let. Calvin. Juſt. cap. <hi>20.</hi> Sect. <hi>7.</hi> Edit. <hi>1553.</hi> I have noted the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not divided into Bookes.</note> when he would have them be in the beſt condition. And it was very near indeed to a free State; for the Elders were choſen by lot, equally out of all the Tribes. Thus I have evinced, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> was when firſt formed and orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized into a political body, under a Magiſtracy different from that they had under Kings. Now that it was lawful for them to change this form of Magiſtracy, is evident.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.14, 15. <hi>When thou art come to the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee,</hi> and ſhalt poſſeſs it, and ſhalt dwell therein, and ſhalt ſay, I will ſet a King over me, like as all Nations that were about me: Thou ſhalt in any wiſe ſet him over thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which Text you may ſee.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the power of keeping or parting with their preſent Magiſtracy is put in the peoples will, if thou ſay, <hi>I will ſet a King over me, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That God directs them in a circumſtance for the exception of this power. <hi>Thou ſhalt chuſe one from among thy Brethren, &amp;c.</hi> which regulation of a circumſtance had been in vain, had they not had power to diſpoſſeſs the Magiſtracy then in poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From their actual changing of their Magiſtracy, <hi>Iſrael</hi> choſe them a King when they had <hi>Samuel</hi> for their ſupreme lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate: and <hi>Samuel</hi> had a ſpecial Command from God to yield to them. <hi>Hearken unto the voice of this people, in what they ſhall ſay unto thee:</hi> But (ſay Non-ſcribers) the Lord both by his word and ſign manifeſted his diſapprobation and anger againſt their ſeeking a King,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</note> when they had <hi>Samuel</hi> to their Judge, even to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction. To which I rejoyne, that it was not the change of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy which was the cauſe of that divine anger.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God was angry becauſe they did it in ſuch an unſeaſonable time, when it was ſo inexpedient, they having ſo juſt a Judge as <hi>Samuel;</hi> as is evident, by comparing 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. at the beginning, with the 19. verſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they did it in diſtruſt of divine aſſiſtance, which had helped them by Judges extraordinarily raiſed in time of danger; whereas they then put more truſt in a King of their own chuſing, then in God that alwayes raiſed Saviours for them, as appeareth, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. compared with the 19. before quoted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe they did it out of deſire of the pomp of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117947:10"/> Nations, who were under Kingly Government.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Quia Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mari maliut <hi>[Iſrael]</hi> quam ſorti a Deo immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atè oblatae ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcere. Wendelinus. Chriſt. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi> Theſ. <hi>6.</hi> Zanch. Com. in Hoſ. p. <hi>134.</hi> Diodat. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</p>
                  <p>Regiminis quendam modum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit, quem perſignifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Flavius adverſus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pionem <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> vocari poſſe ait, quaſi ter ejuſmodi ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xeris cujus praeſes rectór<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſolus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſit. De Rep. Hebraeorum. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> Deut. <hi>12.5. 1</hi> Chron. <hi>17.1.</hi> to <hi>14.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Becauſe they would rather be conformed to the Heathen, then acquieſce in what was immediately given them by God. The miſtiming of an action, and doing it upon baſe grounds, may make an action otherwiſe lawful, to become unlawful.</p>
            <p>But (ſay Non-ſcribers) God hath ſometimes diſowned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned expreſly the peoples Act, in ſetting up a Government o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, which hath been <hi>in ſpecie</hi> lawful. To their Teſtimonies out of <hi>Samuel,</hi> (which are 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.8. &amp; 12.16, 17.) I have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered already. Thoſe out of <hi>Joſua</hi> 8.4. &amp; 13.10, 11. ſpeak, the latter of the election of <hi>Saul,</hi> the former of <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> erection. To them all I anſwer, That the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was (as is well noted by <hi>Cunaeus</hi> out of <hi>Joſephus</hi>) a Theocracy, of which God was in a peculiar manner, the Governour and Law-giver. As God would be conſulted in all ceremonials, ſo would he in all great matters of State. <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſs had intimation that in the Land whither they were going, the Lord would chuſe ſome one place to put his name there, when he would have a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Habitation, as well as they had intimation, that then they ſhould have Kings; but yet if <hi>David</hi> (notwithſtanding his enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the private opinion of <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet and his encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of him to the work) had built the Temple, it would have been a building which God would have diſavowed; for God would have the ordering of all circumſtances in that to come from himſelf: he would have no houſe till he had commanded it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. So when <hi>Iſrael</hi> would have had their Magiſtracy changed, they ſhould have conſulted with God firſt, and when your 10. Tribes turned away from the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> they ſhould have asked Councel of God. Becauſe they did not: therefore God ſaith, they ſet up Kings, but not by him; they asked not his advice, but tumultuouſly ruſht into theſe changes, wilfully and obſtinately crying, give us a King and Princes. But to make this ſtretch to all Nations is abſurd, ſince other Nations have not God for their Law-giver ſo particularly, nor can enjoy his immediate anſwers, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> might have done; but are to be guided by the Law of Nature, and the Rules of right reaſon. Thus have I proved that it was lawful for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to change their eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Government for a King, and conſequently, it may be lawful for a people upon good grounds, to change their Kingly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117947:11"/> Government for any other,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Ariſt. Polit. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Ameſi de ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibus conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Lex, Rex, q. <hi>19.</hi> p. <hi>158. 1</hi> Pet. <hi>2.13.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Monarchia ſi justa eſt, Regnum, ſi injuſta, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannis eſt. Deinde ex Tyrannidis destructione naſcitur A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocratia, etc. Tandem in obligarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am definit et. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biverò ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtitia eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qui prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt per mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinem irâ percitam è medio tollitur mutatur oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchia in Democrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, etc.—ſic ſunt tria Magiſtratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um paria, in quorum ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis qui pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or legitimus, qui poſterior, illegitimus rectè cenſetur. Muſculus. loc. com. page <hi>622.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> unleſs they will ſay that only Kingly Government hath a priviledge to be unchangeable, which is an abſurdity that Court Paraſites would hardly own.</p>
            <p>I may adde reaſon to prove this, and I argue,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the definition of a politick body, which is this, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick body is a ſociety of men, according to nature, having in it ſelf an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or ſufficiency for preſervation of it ſelf, conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for being and well-being. Or ſhorter thus. A ſociety ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in it ſelf to all things conducible to well-being, or commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious life. Now the form of Magiſtracy, may oft-times prove the greateſt hinderance to the happineſs and well-being of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick body, and it cannot be a ſociety, having a ſufficiency for all things conducible to its own civil happineſs, had it not a power to remove theſe preſſures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the limitation that is upon the power of the Magiſtrate. The Magiſtrates power is not abſolute, but limited 1. By the will of God. 2. By the will of the People contained in thoſe Lawes and conditions in which the power of rule is founded. Now the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick body hath a <hi>Nomothetick</hi> faculty, and ſo is not properly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Law, but may change and abrogate thoſe Lawes which are hurtful and pernicious, and conſequently may abrogate the forms of Magiſtracy which are pernicious, as well as the Lawes, by which they only ſtand, and in which their power is placed. 3. Forms of Magiſtracy are called the Creatures of men by the Apoſtle, though Magiſtracy <hi>in genere</hi> be the Ordinance of God, yet <hi>in ſpecie</hi> it is the Creature of man, and conſequently may be deſtroyed by them that made it. I ſhall ſhut up the proof of this with the words of a man famous in his Generation. Monarchy if juſt, is a Kingdom, if unjuſt a Tyranny, out of the deſtruction of Tyranny ariſeth Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocracy, in which the Reines are committed to the moſt juſt and prudent among the Nobles: this ends in an Oligarchy, in which a few unwiſe and unjuſt great ones get power. The iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and injuſtice of whom being taken away by the angry multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the Oligarchy is turned into a Democracy, in which all things are ordered by the people, according to their Countrey Cuſtoms, and certain Lawes, the change of this is into an Ochlocracy, in which the multitude take licence to do what they liſt. So there are 3 paires of Magiſtrates in every one of which, the firſt is legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, the ſecond illegitimate. Kingly, Ariſtocratical, Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117947:11"/> Governments are lawful: Tyranny, Oligarchy, Ochlecracy unlawful. You may plainly ſee, he approves of the change of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Governments. Let this be the firſt ſtep to prove, that the meer diſpoſſeſſion of a former Government, cannot make the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Government unlawful to be obeyed or engaged to.</p>
            <p>Now let us go a little more cloſely along with Non-ſcribers.<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page, <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> The Queſtion that is moſt material is not (ſay they) whether a form of Government may be diſpoſſeſt; but whether it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done by them; for if they have unlawfully put out, and ſtill keep out the ſaid lawful Government, then is their power unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gotten and held. I ſhall gratifie them ſo farre as to grant, that it is not alwayes expedient for a people to change their forms of Magiſtracy, <hi>&amp; quod non expedit, quatenus non expedit, non licet.</hi> Let us ſee then how they prove it unlawfully done.<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>20.</hi> Vel de perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na vel de au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centis inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, cum debeat cum primis inquiri &amp; judicari de doctrina, Comment: in Johannem cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> In reference to this enquiry (ſay they) that which will be conſiderable, is not their goodneſs or expediency of the fact, but the warrant and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for it in them that did it; and they that travel about the goodneſs and conveniency of the things, but lead them out of the way: which aſſertion of theirs is an evidence of moſt putid hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie. <hi>Muſculus</hi> notes it to be the practice of Pſeudo-Biſhops to enquire concerning the perſon and Authority of the Teacher, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they enquire the truth or falſhood of their Doctrine. So theſe that keep ſuch a coyle about titular righteouſneſs, deſpiſe real righteouſneſs: they that teach others to keep their Law, through breaking of the Law, diſhonour God. God (who is moſt eminently and exemplarily juſt, who ruleth in the Kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will) is pleaſed to give a reaſon of the diſpoſſeſſion of Powers, drawn principally from their demerits, who govern unrighteouſly.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 40.20.21.</note> The Prophet <hi>Iſaih</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing his Edict for the transferring of the Kingdom from the <hi>Babylonians</hi> to the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> expreſſeth it thus. Thou ſhalt not be joyned with thy Fathers in burial, becauſe thou haſt deſtroyed thy Land, and ſlain thy people, the ſeed of evil doers ſhall never be renouned: prepare ſlaughter for his Children for the iniquity of their Fathers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> that they do not riſe nor poſſeſs the Land, nor fill the face of the world with Cities. And the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> denouncing the diſpoſſeſſion of the Kingly line of <hi>Judah</hi> ſaith, Thine eyes and thy heart are not; but for thy covertouſneſs, and for to ſhed innocent blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he makes the reaſon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117947:12"/> and foundation of the following ſentence.<note place="margin">Ezekiel <hi>21.24, 25, 26.</hi> Plea, &amp;c. pag. <hi>21.</hi> Nec expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur hodie quâ culpâ exsiderint poſſeſſione, quam bonam de ſe ſpem praebeant, quam inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtratione futuros ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimens, quos ſuſceperint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uendos: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na cauſa ſatis fuerit, propin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quus eſt, Rex natus eſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it nativum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uulum, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nique in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtremis habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, cui popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laris ſtatus afflicti, &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipub. funditus collabentis culpa impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur. Exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium: Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe. p. <hi>505.</hi> Truths ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt. p. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ezekiel</hi> alſo threatning the ſame judgement, ſaith, Becauſe you have made your iniquity to be remembred, in that your tranſgreſſion is diſcovered, ſo that in all your doings, your ſins appear, becauſe, I ſay, that ye are come to remembrance, ye ſhall be taken with the hand: And thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wicked Prince of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe day is come, when iniquity ſhall have an end. Thus ſaith the Lord God, remove the <hi>Diadem,</hi> and take off the Crown: this ſhall not be the ſame, <hi>Nebuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> had no lawful ſuperior power over the King of <hi>Judah,</hi> nor the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> over the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi> but the demerits of the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> made their diſpoſſeſſion juſt before God. Theſe Apoſtate Non-ſcribers have oft preſented the late King before God, as a man of blood, as a perjured oppreſſing Tyrane, and yet now he is blameleſs. We never heard, yet alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (ſay they) nor do acknowledge good reaſon or ground (on mans part) for the matters to have been done. Theſe men ſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condemned of themſelves. We may juſtly ſay as <hi>Albertus Kran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zius</hi> ſaith in a like caſe. <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> and his Son, were expelled out of the Kingdom for Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, both of them breathed out threatnings ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inſt them that had exiled them: yet many favour'd them in their deſerved miſery, who deteſted them in their exorbitant Domination. It's not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded now (ſaith he) by what fault they fell out of poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion, what hope of future amendment may be expected, how juſt they will be in governing, by them that have undertaken to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them; but one thing is enough, he is a Kinſman, a King born, he endeavours to recover his native Title. Laſtly, none conſiders to whom the fault of the peoples afflicted State, and of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent utter ruine of the Common wealth is to be imputed. The blood which hath been ſhed by the two laſt Kings, (which a <hi>Scotch</hi> Writer of no mean credit, ſaith to be more then was ſhed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors in the ten primitive perſecutions) the guilt whereof might have lain upon the Nation, might the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Lords and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>joled Commons have had their will: this blood (I ſay) of ſo many precious Saints and Martyrs, as Non-ſcribers have often called them, is now no more regarded by them, then the blood of ſo many Doggs in a time of peſtilence.</p>
            <p>Yet ſince they put the queſtion upon this iſſue, that the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of perſons is requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſite to make an action lawful, I ſhall joyn
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117947:12"/> iſſue with them in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is particular, hoping not to be non-ſuited at the Bar of reaſon. To evidence the want of Authority in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, they lay down this propoſition.<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. Pag. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> If a Government be made up of three Eſtates, every of them being fundamental to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, one of them cannot take away another. I diſtinguiſh of fundamentalneſs, there are two ſorts of foundations. 1. A natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral foundation, as the ground, ſoyle, earth, or native Rock is to an houſe. 2. Art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ficial, as the ſtones, that are firſt laid upon that ſoyle or natural foundation. So there are two ſorts of Eſtates, funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to the conſtitution of every publick body that deſerves to be called free. 1. Thoſe that are originally fundamental, <hi>viz.</hi> a common ſupreme Councel of Deputies, or Repreſenters freely choſen by the people, in whom the power of making Lawes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions and offices reſts. 2. Thoſe that are aſcititiouſly funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, or derivatively, builded up upon the originally fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal eſtate, who have a power judicial or executive committed to them. Thoſe fundamental Eſtates, which are derivatively ſo, may not take away one another; but the eſtate which is properly fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental, may take away the other, and be blameleſs, in caſe of breach of truſt, or abuſe of power entruſted to them.</p>
            <p>But Non-ſcribers apprehend t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e powers they ſpeak of to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually Coordinate,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> ſo that the whole force of the ſence of their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is this, Coordinate Powers have no power to take away each other: King, Lords, and Commons, are coordinate Powers: <hi>Ergo.</hi> I deny both propoſitions, and ſhall ſhew firſt, the errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Minor. In ſo doing I ſhall ſhew them, 1.<note place="margin">Rights of the Kingdom. p. <hi>86.</hi> &amp; ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi paſſim.</note> That the power of the King was not a coordinate power with that of the Repreſentatives of the people, not an abſolute and perfect coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, which appears, 1. From the nature of the Kings power. Our Lawyers divide the powers of this Nation into Original, Judicial, and Executive, and affirm that the Kings power was but executive. To make executive power coordinate with the nomothetical and original,<note place="margin">Rights of the Kingdom. p. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> were to make the Executioner equal with the Law-maker. 2. From the Coronation-Oath, wherein the King ſware fealty to the State and Lawes, as his higher Lords, that I may ſpeak, as the Authour of the Rights of the Kingdom: in which Oath the King ſware to hold and guard,<note place="margin">Soveraign Power of Parliaments, part, <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> confirm and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Lawes which the Commons ſhould chuſe. <hi>De tuendo &amp; cuſtodiendo juſtas Leges &amp; conſuetudines Eccleſiae, ac de faciendo per ipſum Domirum Regem, eas eſſe protegendas, &amp; confirmandas,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117947:13"/> quas vulgus juſte &amp; rationabiliter elegerit,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> gives us that clauſe of the Kings Oath, out of a Parliament Roll, and out of the Book of <hi>Clarencieux Hanley,</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus, <hi>Will you grant, fulfill &amp; defend all rightful Laws &amp; Cuſtoms which the Commons of the Realm ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll chuſe?</hi> The King ſhall anſwer; <hi>I grant and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That power cannot be coordinate with the Law giving power, which is obliged to all, and cannot alter an apex or Title of thoſe Lawes that another Eſtate ſhall chuſe.</hi> The mutual ſtipulation between King and people,<note place="margin">Appendix. page <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> was that which was conſtituted; a King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> before this paſt, he was but <hi>Regni candidatus.</hi> Non-ſcribers tell us that the Kings of this Realm are legally and actually Kings, upon the death of their reſpective Predeceſſors, and this (ſay they) Lawyers and Hiſtorians will ſatisfie; among whom they choſe <hi>Speed</hi> to urge; in which quotation (I profeſs) I admire, that men brought up in the ſtudy of good Arts, (to ſay nothing of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience they pretend to) ſhould ſo over-ſhoot themſelves, as not to be able to diſtinguiſh between what <hi>Speed</hi> relates as an <hi>Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Speed. Rich.</hi> 1. S. 3.</note> and what corrupt gloſſes he put upon our ancient Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; for immediately before the paſſage they quote, he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges that before <hi>Richards</hi> Coronation; moſt writers call him not a King, and then he holds that Sycophantical gloſſe, which Non-ſcribers make uſe of. A Lawyer, and that a friend of their own, tells us from <hi>Walfingham</hi> (a farre more authentique Hiſtorian then the Merchant-Taylor) that in the Coronation of <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d. when the King had taken his Oath, <hi>Archiepiſcopus praecedente eum, &amp;c.</hi> the Arch Biſhop (<hi>Henry Percy</hi> the Marſhal of <hi>England</hi> going before him) turned himſelf to all the parts of the Church, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the people with the Kings Oath, asking them whether they would obey ſuch a Prince? and it was anſwered by all the people; with a loud voice, that they would; which cuſtom (ſaith he) hath bin conſtantly before and ſince obſerved. And another of his profeſſion ſaith,<note place="margin">Soveraign power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, part. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> That the King ought to take his Oath, before he ſhould require his Subjects homage, &amp; when any Subjects have ſworn homage, before the King had done his homage &amp; ſworn fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to the State &amp; Law, it hath been obſerved by Hiſtorians, as ſome kind of Comet or Prodigy in State-politiques, ſo that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,<note place="margin">Rights of the Kingdom. p. <hi>32</hi>
               </note> that for peace ſake, the next of the blood hath uſually ſucceeded; yet he could not require homage before he had firſt ſworn to the Lords, the Commons, &amp; conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quently hath his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing from that ſtipulation. He cannot then be coordinate with them, whoſe ſwearing obedience to the Lawes they ſhall chuſe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117947:13"/> gives him his Kingly power and dignity. 3.<note place="margin">Lex, Rex. queſt. <hi>21.</hi> p. <hi>177. 178.</hi>
               </note> Thoſe who make a King, and have power to unmake him, in point of miſgovernment, muſt be above the King in point of Government: But the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment makes K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs, and Kings make not Parliaments: the Kings power is fiduciary, and put in his hands upon truſt, and muſt be miniſterial, and borrowed from thoſe who put him in truſt, his power muſt then be leſſe. When the King hath received power from them, they have the whole power they had before, that is to make Lawes, and reſigned no power to the King, but to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Lawes, and his convening them is an act of royal duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lex, Rex<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> queſt. <hi>24.</hi> p. <hi>210.</hi>
               </note> all this is Mr. <hi>Rutherford's,</hi> and therefore ſhould take more with Non-ſcribers. And again, the Parliament is coordinate with the King ordinarily; but the coordination on the King's part is by derivation, on the Parliaments part, <hi>originaliter</hi> and <hi>fontaliter.</hi> In ordinary there is a coordination; but if the King turn tyrant, the Parliament is to uſe their fountain power, and that of the Law, <hi>Par in parem non habet poteſtatem,</hi> is no better from his pen (ſaith Mr. <hi>Rutherford,</hi>) that is from the excommunicate Biſhops of <hi>Roſſe,</hi> then from <hi>Barclay, Grotius, Arniſaeus, Blackwood, &amp;c.</hi> We hold the Parliament that made the King at <hi>Hebron,</hi> to be above their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the King. See then (Reader) who are the Patriarchs and Prophets of Non-ſcribers, faſt Cavaliers, excommunicated Prelates. But what ſay Non-ſcribers to this Argument? Even, run them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the height of Cavalieriſme.<note place="margin">Appendix. p. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> The Authour of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement vindicated, ſaith, the people chuſe their Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and they ſet up Kings, who are therefore meerly the peoples Creatures, depend upon continuation of their pleaſures: <hi>Ejus eſt inſtituere, cujus eſt deſtituere.</hi> To this they anſwer, This is ſpoken as if it were undeniably true, that Kings with us have been wont to be ſet up by the Repreſentatives of the people; but we have neither ſeen nor read of any ſuch cuſtome in <hi>England,</hi> we have not any one preſident of a King, created meerly by a Repreſentative. Is this their knowledge of Hiſtories, to which they ſend us elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where for ſatisfaction? Sir <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> calls the Parliament the Repreſentative body of all <hi>England,</hi> wherein every <hi>Engliſhman</hi> is preſumed to be either by himſelf, or by his Proxie. And many Kings have been made by this. Who made <hi>William</hi> the firſt King? his Conqueſt (Non-ſcribers will ſay) was no juſt title, the right ſucceſſive heir of the Crown <hi>Edgar Etheling</hi> ſurviving? who made <hi>William</hi> the 2. and <hi>Henry</hi> the 1. Kings, while their elder Brother <hi>Robert</hi> was alive?</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117947:14"/>
            <p>What Title had King <hi>John</hi> by ſucceſſion, as long as <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Anne,</hi> the Children of his elder Brother <hi>George Frey,</hi> Duke of <hi>Brittain</hi> lived? the latter of which <hi>Anne,</hi> lived in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the third Son of <hi>John.</hi> The Arch-Biſhop <hi>Hubert</hi> at the Coronation of <hi>John</hi> ſpake thus, <hi>Noverit diſcretio veſtra, &amp;c.</hi> Be it known to your diſcretion, that none hath right or any fore title to ſucceed another in a Kingdom, unleſs firſt he be (with invocation for grace and guidance of Gods ſpirit) by the body of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thereunto choſen.<note place="margin">Soveraign power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments. part. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>54.</hi> Rights of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. p. <hi>70.</hi>
               </note> So Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> out of <hi>Hoveden,</hi> to which all the Aſſembly conſented <hi>ſcientes quod non ſine cauſa ſic defini verat</hi> as the Authour of the rights of their Kingdom, out of <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> and <hi>Wendover,</hi> compared with <hi>Hoveden</hi> and others: which Authour tells us, that if <hi>Bracton</hi> and <hi>Fleta,</hi> 2 ancient Judges, may be made Judges of our Kings Titles, they will tell us that in their times our Kings were elective. And one of them lived in <hi>Henry</hi> the thirds time, the other ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at after. <hi>Edward</hi> the 3. was made King by the ſame power that his Father was depoſed by, and what that was,<note place="margin">Speed. Ed. <hi>2.</hi> S. <hi>74.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Speed</hi> will tell you, the ſentence was pron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unced by <hi>William T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſſel,</hi> of all the men in <hi>England,</hi> and of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Procurator.<note place="margin">Fractus Temporum. part. <hi>7.</hi> Rich. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. was choſen and made King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by the people, for the rightful manhood they found in him, as the old <hi>Fructus Temporum.</hi> But to conclude, who made <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. King? not ſucceſſion; for by his Father he was a meer ſtranger to the Royal Line, and by his Mother of ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>prout of the Family of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> as was excluded from ſucceſſion to the Crown, by that Law which made it capable of ſucceeding to ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Inheritances,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Speed. Hen.</hi> 7. S. 1.</note> as <hi>Speed</hi> confeſſeth. By his wife he had it not; for he exerciſed all the Acts of Royal Power before he was marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. His Conqueſt Non-ſcribers will deny to be a Title, it muſt then follow,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Speed. Rich.</hi> 3. S. 53.</note> that it was from the Parliament he had his Title, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they will ſay (with <hi>Speed</hi>) he had it by election of the people in the field at <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſworth:</hi> But I believe, Non-ſcribers will ſay that Act was more valid, which was done by an orderly Parliament, then that which was done by the Souldiers in the height and heat of their victory. If they have not ſeen or heard theſe things, they are ſtrangers in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtory. But it was not the obſcurity of theſe things in our Hiſtories, that made them ſay thus; but to make the King abſolute ſupreme, and giver of life and being to Parliaments, as is evident from that of theirs; we have no ground
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117947:14"/> to think Repreſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tatives an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecedent to Kings,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Appendix page <hi>35.</hi> Lex. Rex. queſt. <hi>21.</hi> page <hi>177</hi> Lex, Rex. queſt. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>19.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Námque munus illud, quâ vi, quâ gratiâ &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vore, imo quo pretio deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> et corruptelâ, pro temporum hominumque conditione, &amp; ſub ſpecie feudi, aliiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> diverſis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textibus, in peculium tandem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſum est, &amp; ex tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rario haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarium fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum. Guicc: Deſcrip. Hannoniae. p. <hi>440.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nunc nullus in honorum nominibus eſt modus, neque praeter ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem titulum, ullus Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num uſus, Buchanan, Rerum Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticarum. lib. <hi>6.</hi> Verſtegan. cap. <hi>10.</hi> Rights of the Kingdom. p. <hi>9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </note> which is the rotten ground of <hi>Ferke,</hi> the Authour of <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſoria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um,</hi> &amp;c. as Mr. <hi>Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> will tell them Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in, they tell us that the Peoples conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vernment, either collectively or by Proxies by way of election and conſent, is no valid argument of any ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent power in the people to make or unmake Kings. To this I ſay, that the people do not conſtitute their Governours by a bare election and conſent; but they are their efficient cauſe, and give them their civil power and agency. Kings and other Magiſtrates are the effects of the people, and therefore inferiour to them. This nail is driven home to the head by the fore-named, learned <hi>Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> they know the common principle, <hi>Quod efficit tale eſt magis tale;</hi> and for their compariſons of Servants and Paſtors, I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to the place quoted in the Margin, where they may be ſatisfied. 2. The Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were not coordinate with the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the people: I ſhall not ſtay (for I ſhall ſoon diſmiſs them) here to relate the firſt riſing of the like dignities in other places. That learned Hiſtorian <hi>Guicciardin</hi> tells us, that after <hi>Lotharius</hi> the Emperor had divided the Empire into three parts among his three Sons, they out of fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath, began to give up divers Lands to their Palatines, who before were as Judges, ſent to govern them, and from hence came up ſo many Earles, as now we ſee, what by force, what by favour, what by price and corruption, under divers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts the Offi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Palatines was turned into a propriety, and of temporary became hereditary. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſhall I inſiſt upon honeſt and learned <hi>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rge Buchanan's</hi> verdict concerning this kind of men, who informs us that <hi>Malcolme</hi> the 2. was the firſt who brought the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> rather for vain ambition then any uſe, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards complains, There is now no meaſure in new names of honour, and no uſe of their names, beſides the empty Title. To come to our own Lords, The Dukes which were among our <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Anceſtors, I cannot conceive to be any other then the <hi>Hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chii,</hi> that are mentioned in the Confeſſors Lawes, who were the Captains of the Kingdoms Militia, choſen by the people in their Folcmotes; for <hi>Hertzog</hi> is the tearm by which the <hi>Dutch</hi> (of whom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Saxons</hi> were a branch) expreſs a Duke to this day: a word derived from <hi>Here</hi> an Army, and <hi>toge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to lead, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſing the <hi>Latine Dux,</hi> the fountain of our word Duke. <hi>Earle</hi> a name of honour, as <hi>Grave,</hi> of Age, was wont to denote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them the principal Judge of a ſhire, which was alſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117947:15"/> The <hi>Norman</hi> brought in the Title Baron, and the <hi>Norman</hi> Barons, were nothing elſe but the great Free-holders of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. All the Peers are ſaid by Lawyers to ſit in the houſe as Barons, in which right the Biſhops alſo ſat, as being Barons by tenure: as alſo other Barons were before any was ſo by Pattent, which man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Creation, <hi>viz.</hi> by Pattent is not much elder then <hi>Edward</hi> the 3. and indeed, was one of the prime plots of our Kings, whereby they ſtrengthned their Tyranny: they ſaw the great Free-holders that were Barons by tenure, were vigorous Patrons of the peoples Liberties: they therefore gratified many of their own Creatures with Pattents for that Honour, that they might gratifie them with their mercinary Votes. Now, the moſt, if not all of the Lords, were no other then the Kings Pattentees, whereof ſome had bought their Title, others were called to it, to draw them off the ſervice of the Common-wealth, as <hi>Strafford, Digby, &amp;c.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers raiſed out of the Kings private affection, ſo that they were no other then bubbles, blowen up by the breath of exorbitant prerogative. Theſe things premiſed, I ſhall demonſtrate, that the Lords were not coordinate with the Commons by 3. <hi>mediums.</hi> I. The power which they had was but Judicial, and that over the <hi>King</hi> onely.<note place="margin">Soveraign power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments. part. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>5.</hi> in the Margin.</note> 
               <hi>Rex non habet ſuperiorem in terris praeter Deum &amp; Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem &amp; Curiam Comitum &amp; Baronum, qui ideo dicuntur Comites, quia ſunt ſocii Regis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bracton,</hi> quoted by Mr. <hi>Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> and their Office is that <hi>debent ei fraenum ponere.</hi> Nay, the laſt <hi>King</hi> in a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of his (as I well remember I have read, though now I have it not at hand) ſaith, that the Lords were as bankes between him and the Commons, to reſtrain the exceſſes of prerogative. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative power at the firſt they had none, &amp; ſhould we grant that ſince their good ſervices for the people, they had a ſhare of legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power allowed them, yet this would not prove them coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with the Commons. For, the <hi>modi</hi> of Parliaments (ſaith an able Lawyer) will not only tell us, that the Commons have better and ſtronger Votes then the Lords,<note place="margin">Rights of the Kingdom. p. <hi>88.89, 90.</hi> Idem, Ibi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> p. <hi>82.</hi>
               </note> but that there may be a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament without the Lords, which he proves and defends againſt Objections. Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uthour tells us, that the Lords loſt this Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial power, by accepting Pattents from the King, and ſo becoming incorporate with him, his perſonal Commiſſioners, who was not able to conſtitute Judges, when himſelf was a party.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:117947:15"/>
            <p>Nay, ſhould I grant, that Power to the Houſe of Lords,<note place="margin">Non ſecus ac Patronus, cum clientis adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſario de quota litis pactus, ſi Clientis cauſam prodidiſſet, ſi minimè noceret, non poteſt ita ſanè iſta Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num necémque populi inita con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratio, quidqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ejus juri detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here: Verum &amp; illi in poenam le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis quae in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicatores lata eſt incident, &amp; his ac ſi res om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino integra eſſet, &amp; Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num alium eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, &amp; jus ſuum denu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequi Lex per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit. <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae contra Tyrannos. Quaeſt. 3. pag. 98. Rights of the Kingdom, p. 87.88. Valer. Max. li. 2. cap. 2.</hi> Antiquitus [Tribuni Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis] ante valvas poſitis ſubſelliis decreta patrum perpendebant, &amp; ſi quae ex iis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probâſſent rata eſſe non ſinebant. <hi>Janus, Guliel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus de Magiſt. Pop. Rom. ca. 14. So, Lipſius de Magiſt. Pop. Rom. cap. 15.</hi>
               </note> that they were by office the Patrons of the people againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undations of Tyrannie, yet will not this make them coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with the Commons. The means are ſubordinate to the end. The Patron is but an honorary ſervant to his Client. As, if a Patron, having bargained with his Clients adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for a ſhare of the profits, ſhould betray his Clients cauſe, he would not hurt his Clients rights; So, the conſpiracie of great ones to the hurt and deſtruction of the people, cannot detract any thing from the Peoples right; They will fall into the puniſhment the Law ordains againſt prevaricators, and the Law will permit the people to chooſe another Patron, and purſue their own right. Thus <hi>Junius Brutus.</hi> If the Houſe of the Lords then refuſe to judge <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Army publick Enemies, if they continue in a deſtructive Treaty with a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, their Judiciall power which themſelves deſert is loſt: The legiſlative power may deprive them of that power for the future.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Fountain of this power conſidered will ſhew them not to be coordinate with the Commons. The fore-praiſed Author, out of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Antiquities, and an old Law-book called, <hi>The Mirror,</hi> ſhews, that the Lords were raiſed out of, and by the Commons; of late they have been made by the King. Now if the King be not coordinate with the Repre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenters of the People, much leſſe can they be that have their Honor from him. The Kings of <hi>England</hi> heretofore have been conſtrained by Parliament, to leſſen the number of their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Servants. And, although the late Kings might be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated to make muſhrom Lords to furniſh out a Court-jigge, or a Coronation-Pomp; yet could they make none to equall them, who gave Laws to them both, the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> 3. The Lords ſate in a perſonall capacitie onely, not ſo much as repreſenting their own Families, thence were their Brethren and Sons Members of the Houſe of Commons, as <hi>Denzill Hollis, Nathaniel Fienes,</hi> &amp;c. So many ſingle Perſons can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not equall the Repreſentives of the whole people. The Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> (who had a greater power then the Houſe of Lords) were not equal to the Colledge of the Tribunes of the people.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:117947:16"/>
            <p>Neither ſhould we grant, that there were an equalitie of Power between the King, Lords and Commons, would it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that therefore they have no power one over the other. There are exceptions from the generall rule, <hi>Par in Parem non habet poteſtatem.</hi> Neither will their <hi>Major</hi> be firm ſhould we keep the terme coordinate: For, 1. The End of Coordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Powers, is, that if one ſhould prove pernicious to the Common-wealth, there might not be wanting a Power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain it, and if neceſſity require the taking of it away, there might be a face of publick Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity remaining. 2. Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors may become obnoxious to their Inferiors, when by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract they make themſelves ſo. Much more may coordinates become obnoxious to each other, if they be all bound to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuc one end and ſome prevaricate. 'Tis to be confeſt indeed that ordinarily Coordinates have no privitive power over one another, but yet the Rule holds not in all caſes, where one Coordinate endeavors to deſtroy the End for which it was ordained, the other Coordinate may remove it. The End of both their Coordination being to be preferred before the means conducing to it, and it being (not onely dangerous to let the remedie fall into the hands of the multitude, but) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for the innocent coordinate to quit his ſtation. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the great,<note place="margin">Pari poteſtate praediti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> notum verò eſt, quod vu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>go dicitur, Par in parem non habet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium; nibil-ominus tamen Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tantinus Licinium, Chriſtianos, in iiſque nobiles plaeroſque reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis ſive cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sâ, ſive prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textu, re egan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, divex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antem, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trucidantem, bello pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, religionis liberum cultum Chriſtianis vi impetrat, fidem deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> frangentem &amp; ad priſtinam ſaevitiam revertentem Theſſalonicae morte mulciari jubet. <hi>Vindiciae contra Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannos. Quae. 4. pag. 204.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Licinius</hi> were both of them Emperors in one Common-wealth, of equall power, and that vulgar ſaying is well known, <hi>Par in parem non habet poteſtatem;</hi> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, when <hi>Licinius</hi> baniſhed, vexed, killed many Chriſtians, and among them many Noble ones, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their Religion, or under that pretence, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> waged war upon him, by force procures for the Chriſtians free exerciſe of their Religion, and at laſt puts <hi>Licinius</hi> to death at <hi>Theſſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nica,</hi> who had broken his promiſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his former cruelty; ſo <hi>Junius Brutus,</hi> who alſo adds, that when the Empire was divided between <hi>Conſtantines</hi> three Sons, and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the eldeſt maintained the <hi>Arrians, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans</hi> the yongeſt the orthodox, the yonger threatned the elder to force him to reſtore <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> whom he had baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb facs="tcp:117947:16"/> The Conſuls were ſet up at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ne poteſtas ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine corrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peretur.</hi> Florus l. 1. c. 9. Suet. in Julio, cap. 49. Plea, &amp;c. p. 21.</note> leſt a power without companion ſhould turn to Tyranny, the Conſuls therefore were coordinate, yet, when <hi>Caeſar</hi> affected Tyranny, his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legue <hi>Bibulus</hi> proſcribed him, and had he had ſtrength would, doubtleſſe, have executed the ſentence he pronounced.</p>
            <p>But yet there is another ſtumbling block. Thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the King and Lords are not an Houſe of Commons, they are but a parcell of one of the Eſtates, the majority being excluded by them, and kept from them by force of Arms.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer. 1. By denying that the Houſe did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Members that were excluded at the firſt, the force that was uſed in excluſion of them, was not by the conſent of their fellow-Members, as appears by their Meſſage to the Generall and Councell of War. Neither doth the omiſſion of the proſecution of the Authors of it argue their conſent. The puniſhment of an Error (ſuppoſe that this we ſpeak of be one) may be omitted by Authority, if ſuch puniſhment be danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Publick Peace,<note place="margin">Page 9. 10.</note> but of this the <hi>Exercitation</hi> Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpeaks ſufficiently. 2. By denying that they are kept out by force, but by Order of the Houſe, which hath power to puniſh its offending Members. The majority of the Houſe that followed the King to <hi>Oxford,</hi> were excluded by Vote. The Houſe paſt ſeverall Votes to exclude them that would not take the <hi>Covenant,</hi> yet none ever queſtioned the remaining part to be an Houſe, unleſſe it were the <hi>Oxford</hi> Cavaliers. The majority of the Lords Houſe were excluded by Vote,<note place="margin">Petition of 12500. &amp;c.</note> and kept out by the minor part, and yet the <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Miniſters call this minor part, <hi>The Houſe of Peers,</hi> in their Petition, and their Anſwer received <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 25. 1646. the Anſwer of the Houſe of Peers. And, I can conceive no reaſon, why the excluſion of ſome Members out of the Houſe of Commons ſhould make them no Houſe, and the excluſion of the major part of the Houſe of Peers not make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem no Houſe, unleſſe it be, that <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> have forſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken their former principles. But,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. p. 23.</note> this Vote by which the majority was excluded, was contrary to the Vote of that majority, therefore they were unjuſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. Lend me this argument, and but ſuppoſe that the majority of the Lords and Commons that followed the King to <hi>Oxford,</hi> had had the hearts to have ſtayed in the Houſes, till
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117947:17"/> by the moſt voices they could have Voted it unlawfull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the King though he turned Tyrant, and I can by the ſame prove all our defenſive wars to be unlawfull.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Potior ſaniòr<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pars, alteram compeliere in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotio aperto po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</hi> De jure Magiſt. in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos. Quaeſt. 7 Seaſonable Teſtimony againſt Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, p. 12.</note> Meliority not majority is in this caſe to be reſpected. The Vote which was thus diſanulled was, That the Kings Conceſſions in the <hi>Iſle of Wight</hi> were firm grounds for the Eſtabliſhment of the Peace and ſafety of the Nation. Of which Conceſſions the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> was this, <hi>The Lord is highly diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with thoſe proceedings in the Treaty at Newport in reference to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Covenant:</hi> Concerning which they accepted of ſuch Conceſſions from his Majeſtie, as being acquieſced in were dangerous and deſtructive to both. And, <hi>Non-ſubſcribers</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny that in the Propoſitions that were made to the King there,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Simp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Cobler,</hi> page 58.</note> the King was ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uffered to have continued his Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive voice, ſo long oppoſed. Now the Kings <hi>Adviſera</hi> was (as a now friend of theirs expoſtulates) the <hi>Gravamen</hi> of the Nation, to Religion and Peace. Indeed, to grant it were to ſuffer a King to be as abſolute as the great <hi>Turk:</hi> there being no way to eſtabliſh a neceſſary Law, if a wilfull King ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, no way to eſtabliſh the ſafety of a Nation, if he muſt ever have the liberty to pretend diſ-ſatisfaction, and ſay he would adviſe, when State-danger cals rather for action then Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. To conclude, it had been to give away the legiſlative power, and to looſe the King of his obligations at Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Si Regibus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potenter graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantibus &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili p ebeculae inſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tantibus conniveant, eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem nefariâ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erfidiâ non ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere affirmem: quia populi li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatem cujus ſe Dei ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione autores poſitos norunt, fraudulenter produnt. <hi>Inſt. ca. 20. §. 30.</hi>
               </note> wherein he ſwore to defend and confirm the Laws <hi>quas Vulgus elegerit Calvin</hi> will tell them what popular Magiſtrates are that collude with a Tyrant. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they connive at Kings impotently oppreſſing, and trampling on their poore people, I ſhould affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m that this diſſimulation wants not wicked Treachery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they fraudulently betray the Liberty of the people, of which, by the ordinance of God, they know themſelves to be appointed Defenders.</hi> The prevarication of excluded Members in receiving ſuch Conceſſions as were deſtructive to Religion and Liberty, and voting them ſufficient grounds for the eſtabliſhing of both, could not deprive the innocent Members of their power of voting. Injury cannot take away a right. The revolting of abundance of the Members now from the intereſt of the Common-wealth, can no more invalidate the Right of the others, then the flying of ſo many to <hi>Oxfrrd,</hi> as made a mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grel
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117947:17"/> Parliament there, could take away the right of them that remained at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> So that (notwithſtanding what the <hi>Plea</hi> hath ſaid to prove the contrary) the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons is ſtill a whole Houſe legally, which, <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> might be proved. 1. Becauſe they are in number above what the Law acknowledges an Houſe. 2. Becauſe they have a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full call from the people to be their Repreſenters, unrevoked. 3. Becauſe they never gave their conſent to their diſſolution. 4. Becauſe the Law by which they ſit is unrepealed: And nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a face from without, nor the prevarication of their own Members can make them ceaſe to be an Houſe.</p>
            <p>Thus it being p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oved that the King, Lords and Commons were not coordinate, and that granting they were coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, yet in caſe of neceſſity faulty coordinate powers may be excluded from truſt by their coordinates, it will follow that the Power that diſpoſſeſſed the King and Lords is warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, notwithſtanding what hitherto <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> have ſaid to prove the contrary.</p>
            <p>But it was not the Houſe of Commons,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page 23.24.</note> that did En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct the removal of the King and houſe of Lords (ſay <hi>Non ſcribers</hi>): be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that is contrary to the Engagements of the ſaid Houſe in their Declarations. To this I anſwer. 1. By the ſame reaſon, it was not the Houſe of Commons that voted a Treaty with the King at <hi>Newport,</hi> becauſe it was contrary to their Votes of Non-addreſſes, and the Reaſons given in their Declaration to the whole Nation, and their Engagement to ſettle the State without him. 2. What was properly fundamental in our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the Houſe doth maintain, what was artificial or adventitious their being the Supreme Law-givers of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, bound them to abrogate if they found it dangerous to the peoples ſafety and liberty, notwithſtanding their Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That Magiſtrates are bound to prefer the ſafety of the people before any other Engagements of their own,<note place="margin">K. <hi>James</hi> his Declaration in the introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Archbiſhops triall. pag. 47.</note> King <hi>James</hi> is a Witneſſe, his Majeſty intends really to perform what he hath promiſed, the ſuſpenſion of the Laws againſt his Catholick Subjects, but with this Proteſtation, that if they abuſe his favour to the embroyling of his State and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſafety of the Common-wealth is in this caſe <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prema Lex,</hi> and his Majeſtie muſt, notwithſtanding his Oath
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117947:18"/> proceed againſt the offendors, &amp;c. 3. The Declaration of <hi>April</hi> 17.16.6. ſaith, Our intentions are not to change the Ancient form of Government, but to attend the end of the primitive inſtitution of all government: which onely infers thus much: That they would not make any change in the Government, if they could without it keep the Nation in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; but infers not, that when that Eſtabliſhed government came in competition with the Peoples ſafety, they either might not, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would not change it. 4. All your other Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies infer nothing elſe, but, 1. That the Commons truly and ſeriouſly deſired the late Kings ſafetie, and the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his Government, if it might conſiſt with the good of the people that entruſted them. 2. That they were unwilling to make any change, till they ſaw all other means of the Peoples ſafetie un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffectuall. 3. That they did not out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bition ſeek the Kings life, or depoſing (as he and his Cavaliers charged them) but onely the preſervation of them that entruſted them. All which are far ſhort of making this concluſion, Therefore they did not, or had no power to take away abuſed Royalty and Domination, although it were never ſo pernitious to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Nor will their Teſtimonies out of the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mies Declarations, ſtand them in that ſtead,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plea, &amp;c.</hi> p. 25.</note> which they ſuppoſe. 1. The Army (ſay they) confeſſes that their breaking the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons was irregular. To which may be anſwered, 1. That confeſſed irregularity cannot take away the Right of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Members. 2. That whatſoever is irregular is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently unlawfull.<note place="margin">Matth. 12.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Davids</hi> eating the ſhew-bread was irregular, but not unlawfull. Man's Laws muſt all ſtoop in caſe of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the divine Law of Nature, and to the ſafety of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Quoniam, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, Conſul dum juris ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſequitur, id agit ut c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> omnibus Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Romanum imperium cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruat, egomet privatus volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati veſtrae me Ducem offero.</note> the Supreme Law. When <hi>Gracchus</hi> endeavoured to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the <hi>Romane</hi> State, &amp; the Conſul <hi>Scaevola</hi> refuſed to oppoſe him by force, <hi>Scipio Naſica</hi> ſaid, becauſe the Conſul, while he followes the ordinary courſe of Law, ſuffers the <hi>Romane</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire with all its Laws, to be in danger of periſhing, I a private man will be your Captain; &amp; accordingly (though a private man) he repulſed <hi>Graechus</hi> with his complices. So <hi>Scipio Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> when the publique treaſury ſhould have been opened, for the neceſſary uſe of the Common-wealth, and the <hi>Quaeſtors,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:117947:18"/> becauſe they did think it forbidden by Law, refuſed it;<note place="margin">Valer. Max. li. 3. cap. 2. Valer. Max. li. 3. cap. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Scipio</hi> (Iſay) being a private man took the keyes and opened the Treaſury, and made the Laws ſtoop to the publique benefit. Nor will the irregularity of hindring Magiſtrates from doing unlawfull Acts be leſſe defenſible.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 19.40.45.</note> The peoples act in reſcuing <hi>Jonathan</hi> from <hi>Saul</hi> will juſtifie it. They had profeſſed their ſubjection to <hi>Saul,</hi> yet they hindred him from oppreſſing his ſon who had wrought deliverance in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The Army then might well and lawfully, (though extraordinarily, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore irregularly in reference to ordinary rules) hinder the Members of the Houſe from Voting ſuch a Peace, as would have oppreſt not only one but all our <hi>Jonathans,</hi> who had wrought deliverance for our <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 3ly. Non-ſcribers ſay that the Army affirmed, the Judgement of the Houſe of Commons incompetent and inconcluſive, in their conſtitution, before they were purged. Which may be thus anſwered, That the Army affirmed the Parliament morally incompetent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concluſive at that time, becauſe ſo many had ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo far into the Kings intereſt, as to prefer it before the Publique intereſt, not Politically incompetent and inconclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive.<note place="margin">Soveraigne Power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, part. 2. page 40.</note> There is no reaſon why Non-ſcribers ſhould be angry that the Army calls the Houſe of Commons the Parliament, it is ſuch language as Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> teaches. The Parliament (ſaith he) is elective, conſiſting, for the moſt part, of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall men in every County, City, Burrough, &amp;c. And again, The Parliament conſiſting of the a bleſt men of all Counties,<note place="margin">Soveraigne power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, part. 1. page 39.</note> &amp;c. And in another place, whatſoever the people of <hi>Rome</hi> might do either <hi>Centuriatis comitiis,</hi> or <hi>Tribunitiis,</hi> is and may be done by the Authority of Parliament. The Lords were not elected out of Cities, Counties, Burroughs: Cannot reſemble the <hi>Romane</hi> Comitia: therfore, in Mr. <hi>Prinnes</hi> Judgement, not ſo fitly to be called the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, Non ſubſcribers had ſmall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to parallel the depoſition of the King and Lords,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page 21, 23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Med.</hi> 28.</note> with the Act of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> as they do, borrowing this ſimilitude from the late Tyrant, and fulfilling the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Publiſher of that fine piece of Hypocriſie, <hi>Vota da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, quae Bella negârunt.</hi> For, 1. <hi>Moſes</hi> was innocent in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of his Government, the King and Lords betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117947:19"/> the truſt repoſed in them.<note place="margin">In ſeditione enim, duas om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> partes eſſe neceſſe eſt, quae cum de contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictoriis plerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que certen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us juſtam, alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius injuſtam cauſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequitur. Juſta (inquit Barto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las) quae tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum regimen deponere volet: inju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta, quae ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum. Licita, quae ad bonum publi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, illici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta quae ad pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatum tendit. Itaque, ait Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, quia reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Tyrannicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod non ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur ad bonum publicum ſed privatum regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, non eſt juſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, perturbatio iſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Regni non habet rationem ſeditionis. <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciae contra Tyrannos. Quaeſt. 3. pag. 178, 179. Appendix to Soveraign Power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, page 187.</hi>
               </note> 2. The men that acted then, were not the Supreme Magiſtrate, nor ſo much as coordinate with <hi>Moſes:</hi> The houſe of Commons, the faithful part of them I mean, which are proved before to be legally a Houſe, are the Supreme Magiſtrates. 3. The cauſe was ambition in <hi>Corah</hi> and the reſt: in the Parliament, the ſafety of the people. 4. The Action of <hi>Corah</hi> and his complices was ſedition: but in oppoſing a Tyrant, the Tyrant and his complices are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious perſons. For in ſedition (that I may uſe <hi>Junius Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>) it is neceſſary that there be alwayes two parties, who when they ſtrive about contradictory things, it muſt follow, that the ones cauſe is juſt, the others unjuſt. That is juſt (ſaith <hi>Bartolus</hi>) that would depoſe a tyrannicall Government, that is unjuſt, which would depoſe a juſt Government: That is lawfull, which tends to the Publique good, that unlawful, which tends to a private good only. Therefore, ſaith <hi>Thomas,</hi> becauſe a tyrannical rule which is not ordered to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, but to the private benefit of the Ruler is not juſt, the overthrowing of ſuch a rule hath not the reaſon of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: unto which Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> adds out of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> That it is the Tyrant rather that is ſeditious. As for that place out of the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude,</hi> wherein the error of ſome Chriſtians is paralleld with <hi>Corah</hi>'s ſedition, it makes nothing for <hi>Non-ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi> For, 1. Theſe Chriſtians were meer private men, and the meaner ſort of private men. 2. The Power they would have depoſed was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> underſtands, by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Supreme Power in a Common-wealth; they muſt therefore venter another ſtrain of Criticiſme about that word, as well as they do about <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which when they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, we ſhall tell them that the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> and the People in their Repreſentatives, the Maſters and Makers of thoſe Laws have the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 3. The ſin by the Apoſtle there reproved, is the putting down of all Magiſtracie in generall, not the depoſing of faulty Magiſtrates, or changing inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient forms for thoſe that are better. So that all <hi>Non ſcribers</hi> big words are but <hi>bruta fulmina:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> on the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude,</hi> ver. 8.</note> yet the People of <hi>England</hi> might do well to take notice, in what a miſerable caſe their Eccleſiaſtick and Civill Liberties were, if ſuch men's (as <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi>) domination, were not ſtrictly limited, and narrowly confined.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:117947:19"/>
            <p>But what will <hi>Non-ſcriber,</hi> ſay, if I prove that the former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Government of the Nation was not depoſed or diſpoſſeſſed by the preſent power. The conſtitution of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was a multiformed Government, ſay <hi>Non-ſcribers,</hi> and I adde, that if it was a mixture of juſt ſpecies, it was of Royalty, Optima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Polity, properly ſo called. The Powers that were diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt were, Tyranny of a <hi>Scarlet</hi> die the in the late King, Oligarchy in a Company of Pattentee-Lords, and Ochlocracy in the ſeditious Commons, who voted a Treaty with the Tyrant, they complying with the ſeditious <hi>Surrey</hi> and <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Peti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ioners. Now Tyranny, Oligarchy, and Ochlocracy, are ſpecifically different from limited and lawful Royalty, Ariſtocracy and Polity. And conſequently the preſent power diſpoſſeſt a meer novel power. The former Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being diſpoſſeſt by the King turning Tyrant, the Lords accepting Pattents, and the Commons that are excluded, abetting Tyranny and Tumults. Set the Saddle on the right Horſe, and let <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> judge who diſpoſſeſt their former Government. Nay, yet further, the <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> and their beloved party, were they who, even according to their own principles, depoſed the King, Houſe of Lords, and Majority of the Commons. The civil being of a King is in his Royal Power, this <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> Friends had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him, and made him not only leſs then a King, but then a private free-man, their Captive.<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. pag. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> The Majority of the Lords houſe they kept out, and according to <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> principles, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority of a houſe is legally, and as to action and power, the whole houſe.<note place="margin">Familiare eſt hominibus omnia ſibi ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere, nihil aliis remitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; invidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am rerum non ad cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, ſed ad voluntatem perſonáſque dirigere. Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leius Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ol. Poſterius.</note> The like they did by the Commons who followed the <hi>King</hi> to <hi>Oxford,</hi> who were (for ought I can learn) the Majority of that houſe. All theſe things they did by no leſſe force then was uſed in that <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſo much quarrel. It's a familiar practice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſome men, to pardon themſelves in every thing, others in nothing, and to caſt the envy of actions upon other men, which when it ſtood with their own will and advantages they did them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>But go to, let us ſee whether <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> afford us not an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to prove the diſpoſſeſſion of the <hi>King</hi> and Houſe of <hi>Lords,</hi> and his other Adherents lawful. In their <hi>Appendix</hi> they have this paſſage: ſome kinds of Governments are in their own nature unlawful; ſo is that of the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. And the 10. <hi>Kings</hi> [or Kingdoms many underſtand] giving their power and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117947:20"/> ſtrength to the beaſt. Suppoſe now that it can be proved, that the <hi>King</hi> and thoſe who would have reduced him in his impenitency, did give up their power to the Beaſt, (as I doubt not to prove that they did) will it not then follow, that their power was in its nature unlawful? and that it was lawfully diſpoſſeſt, which was a power of its ſelf unlawful and not to be ſubmitted to?<note place="margin">Introduction to the Arch-Biſhops Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al pag. <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> go to then, let us ſee whether the King did not give up his power to the beaſt. I ſhall not here ſtand upon King <hi>James</hi> his Declaration (wherein he undertakes to ſuſpend the execution of all Lawes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Papiſts, and to hinder the making of any more) though publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Prinne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Popiſh Royal Favorite. pag. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> nor upon King <hi>Charles</hi> his Letter ſent from <hi>Spain</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> wherein he not only calls the <hi>Pope</hi> moſt holy Father, but averts himſelf to have been alwayes farre from encouraging of novelties, or being a Partizan of any faction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholique, Apoſtolique, Roman Religion: upon which paſſage Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> notes that our Religion was deemed but a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty and faction by the King.<note place="margin">Truths ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt. p. <hi>20.</hi> Kings Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net opened. let. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>7.</hi> Ibidem. let. <hi>19.</hi> p. <hi>19.</hi> Popiſh Royal Favorite. p. <hi>1.</hi> to <hi>30.</hi> Introduction to the Arch-Biſhops Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. p. <hi>84. 85.</hi> Cabinet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened. let. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> He that diſpatched a Commiſſion under the great Seal of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power them to Maſſacre the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants: He who did give his <hi>Popiſh</hi> Wife Authority in his name to promiſe that he would take away all penal Lawes againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholiques, as ſoon as he was able: He that commanded his Lieutenant in <hi>Ireland</hi> to promiſe the like to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels: He that was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes an uxorious obſerver of a <hi>Romiſh</hi> wife; that hath imployed all his power to free Prieſts and Jeſuites from danger; that to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie their <hi>French</hi> King a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> lent him his Ships againſt the poor Proteſtants of <hi>Rochel,</hi> and hath armed many thouſands of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſts, beſides <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, againſt his Proteſtant Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: He that avoweth his conſtancy to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and all his own &amp; the <hi>Queens</hi> friends, whom <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> have oft called <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts:</hi> the man (I ſay) that hath done all this, hath given his power to the Beaſt: which power he hath by inſtigation of the Beaſts Emiſſaries imployed againſt the Lambe and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. They who would have ſet this man over us again, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proviſion againſt his negative voice, or any taſte of repentance, gave up their power to the Beaſt, in giving themſelves up to him that was the Beaſts Client.<note place="margin">Declaration of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in <hi>Ulſter.</hi>
               </note> Nor is the ſtate now changed, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels is now one with that of the declared Kings of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as they have publickly teſtified to the world. So
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117947:20"/> that all that ſtrive to reduce him ſerve the <hi>Anti hriſtian</hi> Intereſt, and it is remarkable, how the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Non-ſcribers,</hi> agree in their opinions concerning our preſent Government. To conclude, ſuch a power being unlawful in its nature, as <hi>Non-ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> tell us, is lawfully diſpoſſeſt by any that hath the power of a Magiſtrate, and hates the Beaſt, and all that refuſe to exerciſe their power in deſtroying the Beaſts Government, may well be concluded under the curſe of <hi>Meroz,</hi> becauſe they reward not the whore as ſhe hath dealt with the Saints.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Medium</hi> whereby <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> would prove the <hi>Common wealth</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to be an unlawful power,<note place="margin">Coal from the Altar p. <hi>42.</hi> Plea, &amp;c. p. <hi>26.</hi> Ariſt. Polit. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> is in regard of its erection. And here they kindle like Dr. <hi>Cole</hi> againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> for ſaying the Children of the Common-wealth, we live (ſaith <hi>Heylin</hi>) in a Monarchy not under a Democracy. So they cry, at the firſt fight, it looks like that which they call a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracy. If they would have conſulted <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> he would have told them what that is which lookes like a Democracy, and is none; he layes it down as the mark of a perfectly mixt Polity,<note place="margin">Qui concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſanè ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirabilis, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam exprimit laudatam Platoni Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicam, quam opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, cum plebis conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione. Hugo Grotius. De Antiquit. Reipub. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavicae. cap. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>38.</hi> vulgatum eſt nullam fiſco praeſcriptionem nocere, multò verò minus univerſo populo, qui Rege poti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r eſt, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>júſque gratiâ Princepids privilegium habet, Vindiciae contra Tyrannos. Quaeſt. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>96.</hi> Appendix. pag. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> to be ſo mixt of Oligarchy and Democracy, that its doubtful whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the form of the Common-wealth be Oligarchical or Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical. So is the Common-weale of <hi>England</hi> mixt, the peoples election of their Delegates is Democratical, the Government of theſe Deligates is Oligarchical, they being choſen out of the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt of every County: and both theſe put together, make up a Pol ty as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calls it; but as <hi>Plato</hi> (whoſe termes differ from <hi>Ariſtottles</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> To prove the erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this unlawful, they much labour; but that toyl of theirs might very well have been ſpared. The people of this Land have in all ages had a ſupreme power over their King and Lords, which was exerciſed by their Repreſentatives; who by old Lawes were to meet twice a year, and by a latter Statute once a year, though the Tyranny of wicked Kings had brought that of late into a diſuſe. Which preſcription, notwithſtanding, cannot take away the Peoples right. Its vulgarly ſaid, That no preſcription lies againſt the Kings Exchequer, much leſs can a preſcription lie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the People, who are greater then the Prince, and for whoſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117947:21"/> ſake the Prince hath that priviledge,<note place="margin">Dicores qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor eſſe in quibus ſita eſt tota vis &amp; Majeſtas Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipublicae, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirum, Jus Magiſtratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um crean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberationes omnes de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce &amp; de Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, Legum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dèmque Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocationes. Donatus Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nottius de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. Venetâ. pag. <hi>59.</hi> Speed. Book. <hi>5.</hi> Chap. <hi>5.</hi> Suma impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii belli<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrandi, communi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio commiſſa eſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſſivel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi>— No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro adventu commoti Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tani, hunc to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti bello, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rióque praefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerant. Caeſar Commenter. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. <hi>5.</hi> Spe. d. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> S. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Junius Brutus.</hi> The form of Government is that which <hi>dat eſſe &amp; operari,</hi> as <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſay, and natural order and reaſon requires that <hi>propriae operationes propriae formae reſpondeant:</hi> if therefore it be proved, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives have ever had <hi>de jure</hi> a power to do the Acts proper to the ſupreme power, it will follow that the ſupreme power was formally in them, and that they were a Common-wealth, having ſupreme Authority in themſelves. Let me here uſe the words of a learned <hi>Florentine,</hi> I ſay (ſaith he) that there are four things, in which the whole power and Majeſty of every politique body is placed, the power of creating Magiſtrates, all deliberations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Peace and Warre, making of Lawes, and the laſt appeales: If therefore the Repreſentatives of the people have had the right, to create all general Magiſtrates, to conſult of Peace and Warre, to make and abrogate Lawes, and the priviledge of the laſt appeal to be made to them, they have been the ſupreme power. That they have had theſe Rights, I ſhall prove and begin firſt with Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Magiſtrates. <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> (before whoſe entrance into this Iſland, the times are obſcure, through whoſe miſts no <hi>Eagles</hi> eyes can pierce, as the beloved <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> of <hi>Non-ſcribers, Speed</hi> confeſſeth) found the ſupreme power of electing Magiſtrates, in a Common-Councel of the people. The chief power of Rule, and adminiſtring the Warre, was by a Common Councel committed to <hi>Caſſivellau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> And again, the <hi>Brit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ains</hi> being troubled at our landing, ſet him (that is <hi>Caſſivellaune</hi>) over the whole Warre and Empire. The Common Councel then that made <hi>Caſſivellaune</hi> King and General, was a <hi>Tan-Britanicum,</hi> an Aſſembly repreſenting all <hi>Britain.</hi> And when the <hi>Romans</hi> quitted their tooting here, the <hi>Britains</hi> being invaded by the <hi>Picts,</hi> joyntly united their meanes and powers, and with one conſent elect a King to manage thoſe affair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s which was <hi>Vortigerne,</hi> whom afterwards they depoſed and elected his Sonne <hi>Vortimer.</hi> But I muſt for further ſatisfaction in this point refer them to the Authour of the Rights of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who after many Examples of ſuch Creation of Kings, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes thus: We ſee the Law, at leſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtom of thoſe times, both for electing, anointing, judging and executing of Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, among our <hi>Britiſh</hi> Anceſtors. Conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning our <hi>Saxon</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors (ſaith the ſame Authour) the <hi>Minor</hi> is very clear, that they did elect or chuſe their Kings from among themſelves, who well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117947:21"/> therein with the witneſs of <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Rights of the Kingdom. p. <hi>55.</hi> Rights of the Kingdom. p. <hi>35.</hi> Reges ex n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitate, duces ex virtute ſumunt. Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citus de mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manorum.</p>
                  <p>Soveraign Power of Parliaments, part. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p <hi>78.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Soveraign Power of Parliaments. part. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>41.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Soveraign Power of Parliaments. part. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>91.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> who ſpeaking of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Germans</hi> (of whom the <hi>Saxons</hi> were a branch) ſaith, they choſe their Kings for their Nobility, their Leaders for their vertue: which Teſtimony informs us, that they enobled ſome for their vertues, and out of them choſe their Kings. Concerning the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> I have ſpoken already. To conclude with the Teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Prinne,</hi> who tells us, That our Parliament and Kingdom (ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the oppoſition) anciently have both claimed and exerciſed a Supreme Power over the Crown of <hi>England</hi> it ſelf, and that we may be ſure what he meanes by Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iament, in another place he ſaith out of <hi>Forteſcue, Chancellor</hi> of <hi>England in</hi> Henry the ſixth's time, that Kings were created and elected at firſt by the general Votes of the people, from whom alone they receive all their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority, having ſtill no other or greater lawful power then they conferred on them, (only for the defence of Lawes, Perſons, Liberties Eſtates and the Republicks welfare) which they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate, augment, or diminiſh for the common good as they ſee juſt cauſe. Neither did the ſetting of Kings over them, diveſt them of the ſupreme power it ſelf, if Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> (while a defender of Parliaments) may be credited. I doubt not (ſaith he) but our Parliaments, Kings, and all other Nations would ſay, they never intended to erect ſuch an abſolute, eternal, unlimited Monarchy over them, and that they ever intended to reſerve the abſolute, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal, ſoveraign juriſdiction in themſelves, that if their Princes ſhould degenerate into Tyrants, they might have a remedy to preſerve themſelves. An impregnable evidence that the whole Kingdom and Parliament repreſenting it, (obſerve what is a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the Repreſentative of a Kingdom, and then not the Lords that repreſent no body) are the moſt Soveraign power, and above the King, becauſe having the ſupreme juriſdiction in them at firſt, they never totally transferred it to the King, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it in themſelves. I ſhould tire my Reader, ſhould I ſay all that might be ſaid concerning the Commons Creation of other Magiſtrates.<note place="margin">Soveraig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Power of Parliaments. part. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> brings in Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cook,</hi> affirming, that the Lord Chancellor, Treaſurer, privy Seal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Lord chief Juſtice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Privy Councellors, Heretoches, Sheriffs, with all Officers of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and Conſtables of Caſtles, were uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly elected by the Parliament, to whom of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent right their election belonged, who being commonly ſtiled the Lord <hi>Chancellor,</hi> Treaſurer, chief Juſtice, &amp;c. of <hi>England,</hi> not of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117947:22"/> the King, were of right elected by the Repreſentative body of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> to whom they were accountable for their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Rights of the Kingdom. p. <hi>77. 78.</hi>
               </note>2. All conſultations of Peace and Warre, of right appertain to the Commons of <hi>England.</hi> It was the great Councel (ſaith the Authour of the Rights of the Kingdom) that treated with and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Romans</hi> at all times, and when the <hi>Romans</hi> could not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the <hi>Britains</hi> feare, it was this that called in their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours firſt, and after the <hi>Saxons.</hi> All military Affairs (ſaith Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi>) of the Kingdom heretofore, have origina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly of right (for their original,<note place="margin">Soveraign power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments. part. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> determining, councelling, diſpoſing part) bin order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Parliament, the Miniſterial only by the King. The Act of 28. <hi>E.</hi> 1. ſettles the Militia in the ſubject (ſaith Mr. <hi>Derham</hi>) and addes, the abſolute and general power of the Militia, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia poſitive or regulated by poſitive Lawes,<note place="margin">Manuel of the Rights of Parliament. p. <hi>95. 98.</hi>
               </note> are both by Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in the people, or the Repreſentative body, the Parliament. And again, the ſame Authour (whoſe whole book tends to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the ſupreme power of the Peoples Repreſentatives) ſaith, We may ſafely conclude, that the Subjects right, and conſequently of their Repreſentative body to diſpoſe of the Militia and great Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Kingdom, remaineth yet undoubted to this day. In a word, neither King nor Lords, joyntly nor ſeverally, had any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to mould or manage a new Militia, or raiſe a man, or leavy a farthing towards the payment of an Army, before the Commons by their Legiſlative power had decreed a Warre, the proportion of Men and Horſes to be raiſed, and of money to be leavied, ſo that though we grant the King and Lords as Heretoches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to have had an executive power, as General, Colonels, Captains, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet the Commons ever had power to decree Peace and Warre, and the ſupreme power over theſe their Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The intereſt of the Commons in the ſupreme legiſlative power, hath been evidenced already out of the Coronation-Oath, to which may be added that of <hi>Forteſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Soveraign Power of Parliament. part. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> quoted by Mr. <hi>Prinne.</hi> The King who is head of that politique body, cannot change the Lawes of that body, neither can withdraw from the ſaid people their proper ſubſtance, without their wills and conſents; for ſuch a King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f a Kingdom politique, is made and ordained for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe of his Subjects Lawes, and of their Bodies and Goods, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he receiveth power of his people, ſo that he cannot govern
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117947:22"/> his people by any other Law.<note place="margin">Rights of the Kingdom. pag. <hi>89.</hi>
               </note> The Authour of the Rights of the Kingdom tells us, that if we look to the old Writ of Summon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, we ſhall find the Commons called <hi>ad conſentiendum &amp; faciendum;</hi> and the old Writ added, <hi>quod quilibet &amp; omnes de Comitatu facerent, vel faceret, ſi perſonaliter intereſſent,</hi> as it is in the <hi>modus</hi> of <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,</hi> with ſufficient intimation, that without the Commons no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be done: which the late Writ expreſſes thus, <hi>Ita ut dicta negotia infecta non remaneant pro defectu poteſtatis:</hi> but the Lords are called, <hi>de quibuſdam arduis tractaturi &amp; conſilium impen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuri, &amp;c.</hi> only as <hi>Councellers,</hi> not as <hi>Law-makers;</hi> for the very ſame words are in the Writs for <hi>Judges</hi> and others coming to <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> although they do not vote in making Laws.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Soveraign power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, p. <hi>47.</hi> &amp; <hi>51.</hi> of the firſt part.</p>
                  <p>Ibidem. part. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> And if it ſhould be replyed, that Statutes are ſaid to be enacted by the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> as well as the <hi>Commons,</hi> I ſhall anſwer, that the <hi>Kings</hi> conſent is required <hi>ex debito,</hi> by vertue of his Office, to every Law the <hi>Commons</hi> make, and he cannot alter one tittle of it: nor hath he any negative voice in matters of common Juſtice, and that Laws might have been made if all the Lords had been abſent, as Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> telleth us from <hi>Vowel:</hi> whereas the <hi>Commons</hi> were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound to give conſent to what the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> propoſed, nor could the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> act any thing without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The priviledge of the laſt appeale, was <hi>de Jure,</hi> the right of the <hi>Commons.</hi> Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> calls the Knights,<note place="margin">Soveraign power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. part. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>24</hi>
               </note> Citizens and Burgeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the ſupreme Councellers and Judges of all others, to whom all other Courts, Councellers, Officers, Judges are reſponſible, for their actions, judgements, advice. Appeales a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, either from obſcurity of Lawes, and who ſo fit to interpret Lawes, as they that make them? or from new caſes not yet by Law determined, and then the Legiſlative power muſt only inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: or from the corruption of officers and errors in judgement, and then none are ſo fit to judge as they who have the Fountain-Power, and derive it to all other Officers.</p>
            <p>Thus having ſhewed that the ſupreme power hath appertained of r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght to the Repreſentatives of the people, it will follow that the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is not a thing of yeſterdayes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; but the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> which hath heretofore been, doth now more clearly appear; we have the proper fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls of our moſt ancient Government ſtill ſtanding: the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117947:23"/> or aboliſhing of ſome Offices and names of Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">Commutatis Magiſtratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um nomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis non ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim alia Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publica eſt; dum visſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma imperii primáque poteſtas, &amp; illa, ut ita dicam, mens qua corpus omne movet at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> continet, una maneat at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eadem. Grotius. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Dedic. ante libellum de Anti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipub. Batavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae. Nec eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ip. Romanae concidiſſe quis dixerit, cum exactis Regibus, Majeſtas ad Optimates tranſiret. Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobus Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padius Tract. de Repub. Romano-Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. par. <hi>1. S. 60.</hi> Plea, &amp;c. pag. <hi>27.28.</hi> Plea, &amp;c. pag. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> doth not make a new kind of Government, as long as the ſupreme pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary power, and the ſoule (as I may call it) which moves and quickens the whole politique body, remains one and the ſame. Let no one ſay (ſaith a learned politique Councellor of the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick's</hi>) that the eſſence of the Roman Common-wealth periſhed, when the Kings being driven out, the Majeſty paſſed to the <hi>Optimates:</hi> much leſſe, is a new form of Government erected where the Majeſty remains in the ſame Subjects that ever it did. The Kings power being but executive, the Lords judicial, both but fiduciary and upon truſt, the Common-wealth laying them both aſide for breach of truſt, can no more be ſaid to have chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed its Government and erected a new one, then a Maſter of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily that turns away a waſteful Steward, and ſome other unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants, and fulls thriftily to deconomize himſelf, can be ſaid to change the form and nature of his Fami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y-Government.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid it appeares.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Houſe of Commons had a power to lay aſide the King and Houſe of Lords, in caſe of breach of truſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That their power by taking of them away is not loſt, that houſe being as a ſoule to the body, without whom the King and Houſe of Lords were a liveleſs trunck, and could do nothing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the power which at preſent they enjoy, is that wherewith they were inveſted by the people, when they choſe them to be their Repreſentatives, ſo that their power is not of themſelves, as calumniating Non-ſcribers would perſwade us. Neither will what they quote from the Armies Declaration be of any avail to them. We ſay (with the Army) that the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the ſame Repreſentatives is not fit to be drawn into ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary preſidents, leaſt their power ſhould be corrupted by length of time: yet in times of extraordinary danger, when a great part of the people are diſaffected to the meanes of their own ſafety, and elections are like to be made of ſuch as would return us (it may be) to our former ſlavery, it is not unjuſt that power be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the hands of the preſent faithful Repreſentatives, who yet are not to be looked upon as thoſe that muſt ever, continue in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at power: that which we engage to is to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommon-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> which intimates (as was ſaid before) ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Repreſentatives.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:117947:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> adde to prove the power unjuſt.<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page 30.</note> 1. That it is againſt the Ancient and indubitable legal Rights and Tithes of the King, Prince and Peers, to their reſpective hereditary dignities and powers. To this may be anſwered. 1. That thoſe powers and dignities in their firſt inſtitution were not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary: this hath been proved already. And further, things properly tranſmittable from Father to Son as Inheritances, are onely <hi>bona fortunae;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 23.1. with 1 Chron. 29.22.</note> Kingdoms and dignities are not ſo communicable. <hi>Solomon</hi> was no King till the people had the ſecond time anointed him, notwithſtanding his deſignation by his Father. <hi>Ahaziah</hi> notwithſtanding the death of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and elder Brethren,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 22.1.</note> was not King till the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had made him ſo.<note place="margin">Lex. Rex. Queſt. 10. pag. 76.</note> Nor doth the ſetling the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſucceſſion upon a line by a Law, make the Kingdome the Kings Inheritance. <hi>Arniſaeus</hi> ſaith, that the Son hath not the right of reigning as the patrimony of the people, but as a propriety given him by the Law of the Kingdom by his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; which aſſertion (ſaith Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi>) is all one as if he ſaid, the Son hath not the right of reigning as the patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the people, but as the patrimony of the people, which is good non-ſenſe: for the propriety of reigning given from Father to Son by the Law of the Kingdom is nothing but a right to reign, given by the Law of the people, and the very gift and patrimony of the people. He adds many arguments to prove that Kingdoms go not as a heritage from Father to Son. To whom I may adde <hi>Junius Brutus,</hi> who denies,<note place="margin">Vindiciae contra Tyrannos. <hi>Quaeſt. 3.</hi>
               </note> and that upon good grounds, that the King is either proprietary, or ſo much as the uſufructuary of his Kingdom: much leſſe hath he ſuch an intereſt in it, as a man hath in his Inherit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. An Inheritance may be ſold, pawned, changed,<note place="margin">Grotius. de jure belli &amp; pacis <hi>l. 1. cap. 4.</hi> §. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> none of theſe can be attempted by a King to be done to his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome without loſing his right to it. For the Lords, Mr. <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therford</hi> ſaith, That the King can make heritable Judges more then he can communicate faculties and parts of judging, I doubt. Riches are of Fathers, but not promotion, &amp;c. Honour is properly the reward of vertue, and conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quently not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly communicable to poſterity. Our Lords were at firſt elected by the People, and enobled for their virtues. 2. Though we ſhould grant, that the Kings had the Kingdom, and the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117947:24"/> Lords their dignities as Inheritances, yet the right to an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance may be loſt, may be ſeized. Where God hath not bound conſcience, men may not binde themſelves and their poſterity; but God hath not bound any Nation irrevocable to any Royall line or form of Government: <hi>Ergo,</hi> No Nation can binde their conſcience,<note place="margin">Lex. Rex. que. 10. pa. 78.</note> or the conſcience of poſterity ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to one Royal line, or irrevocably and unalterably to Monarchy.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Superior verò univerſus popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, quíve eum repraeſentant.</hi> Vindicae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Tyrannos, Quae. 3. p. 178.</note> So Mr. <hi>Rutherford. Junius Brutus</hi> tels us that a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant doth <hi>In populum tanquam in Feudi Dominum feloniam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere,</hi> commit Felony againſt the People as againſt the Lord of his fee; and adds from <hi>Bartolus,</hi> that he may be depoſed, and puniſhed by his Superior, and his Superior is the whole people, or they that repreſent them. Treaſon according to our Laws taints the blood, and makes the children of Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors uncapable to ſucceed in any thing of inheritance. The Kings of <hi>England</hi> were as much ſubject to Law as any private Subject.<note place="margin">Soveraign power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, part. 1. pag 34.</note> Though <hi>in exhibendo jure</hi> he were <hi>maximus,</hi> yet in <hi>ſuſcipiendo jure</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bracton</hi> in Mr. <hi>Prinne) minimo de Regno ſuo comparatur.</hi> He was to be obedient to ſuffer right, as well as others of his people, ſaith another Lawyer out of the <hi>Mirror,</hi> an ancient Law-book. No wrong therefore is done to King or Prince,<note place="margin">Rights of the Kingdom, p. 31.</note> they having committed Treaſon againſt their own Crown and dignity, by raiſing war againſt their people, and ſo falling from all right to their hereditary dignities. Had it been true that <hi>Naboth</hi> had blaſphemed God and the King, it had been no ſin in <hi>Ahab</hi> to have ſeized upon his vineyard, though the inheritance of his father. <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> brethren that call themſelves a Pack of old Puritans, ſhew themſelves to be a Pack of Epiſcopaturient Parafites, by their making the King as innocent as <hi>Naboth,</hi> and the Kingdom as much his Inheritance as <hi>Naboth</hi>'s vineyard was to him. The Lords alſo by denying concurrence with the Commons in proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt the Tyrant and his friends, betrayed as much as in them lay the Common-wealth, and therefore are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly removed from that Authority they had. The great Charter ſaith, <hi>Nulli negabimus, nulli vendemus, nulli differemus juſtitiam.</hi> The Lords denying juſtice, broke that which is (if any be) a fundamentall Law of the Nation, and for that are juſtly puniſhed by the Commons their Superiors. A Judge
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117947:24"/> delaying, or denying juſtice, may be deprived of his office, and why not the Lords? whoſe office (if they be not of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thoſe officers who have <hi>nec munus nec uſum</hi>) was judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial onely, as was ſhewed before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is againſt the Houſe of Commons;<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. p. 31.</note> but to prove that they bring nothing but the <hi>crambe bis cocta,</hi> of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of the Declaration of <hi>April</hi> 17. 1646. the putting of the name of the Houſe upon a part, and the proſtitution of priviledges; all which have been ſpoken to already.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is injurious to the people.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plea, &amp;c. ibid.</hi> In civium nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero non ſunt habendi, viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores enim ſunt humanae ſocieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, aut certà proditores. <hi>Buchanan. de Jure Regni apud Scotos.</hi>
               </note> 1. In bereaving them of their Ancient Authority, &amp; impoſing a new, without and againſt their wils. The removal of what authority is taken away is juſtified: no new one is impoſed, as hath been proved. What is done is ſo far from being againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he peoples wils, that the beſt of them rejoyce at it, &amp; praiſe God for it: the reſt that would have colluded with the Tyrant, are not to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Members of any civill ſociety, becauſe they are vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters of, or traytors to humane ſocietie. 2. In debarring from the Houſe of Commons, Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes choſen by them; yet the people were not wronged by debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the Houſe of Commons thoſe that denyed the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. The Houſe may exerciſe Authority over their own Members, without wrong to the people: to whom it is the greateſt bleſſing, to have thoſe puniſhed that would betray them, that truſted them. 3. In bringing things upon them which the Scripture makes a curſe. To this I ſay. 1. That things done by Law, as the Kings execution, and the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Kingly and Lordly power were, cannot be ſaid to be done violently. 2. That all the violence that was uſed was juſtifiable againſt him that violently aſſaulted their Houſe, and raiſed up Arms againſt his Parliament and people. 3. Its no curſe to be freed from a Tyranny, I deny a Tyranny to be a Kingdom. 4. Kingly Rule is not a more eſpeciall bleſſing then any other Government. God when he ſetled <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the beſt condition gave them a Common-wealth:<note place="margin">Num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.6, 17. Luk. 22.25, 26. Rev. 17.12, 13.</note> and Chriſt notes thoſe Nations to be miſerably Lorded over, who had Kings, though ſuch ſlaves, as <hi>Non ſcribers,</hi> called them Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, and tels his diſciples, it ſhould not be ſo among them. Kings are fore-told of as being the horns of the Beaſt, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117947:25"/> that time we are yet under, few Kings being not the Beaſts ſlaves.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mera ſomnia &amp; certa ſigna hominis labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantis febri Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicâ. Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. enervatus.</hi> lib 3. cap. 1. <hi>Rarò in aulis Regum Deo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri juſtum honorem. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorat.</hi> In Matt. 27.14. Hiſtorical vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> part. 1. p. 66. <hi>Voluptatum il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecebris tracti &amp; falsâ ſpecie honoris decepti.</hi> De Jure Regni apud Scotos. G. Buchanan. Epig. lib. 1. De Caſare &amp; Codro.</note> Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> tels <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (who held Monarchy to be the beſt of Governments) that his commendation of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy was an idle and fooliſh ſpeculation, and this his proofs of it (which are ſomewhat like in ſtrength to <hi>Non ſcribers</hi> ſweet ſtuffe) were nothing elſe but meer dreams of one ſick of a Monarchical Fever. <hi>Marlorate</hi> out of <hi>Calvin</hi> notes, that God is ſeldome duly honoured in Kings Courts. Mr. <hi>Cather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> an eminent <hi>Scotch</hi> Divine, the Author of <hi>Altare Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenum,</hi> wrote and publiſhed, that in all Kings naturally there is an hatred to Chriſt: which Mr. <hi>Baily</hi> doth vindicate and approve, though he over-mollifies Mr. <hi>Catherwood</hi>'s ſence. <hi>Buchanan</hi> affirms, that the Kings of his dayes were ſuch as would never yield to be defined by thoſe things that were neceſſary to the definition of a King, and deſcribes them as thoſe that are broken with the allurements of pleaſures, and deceived with a falſe ſhew of honour. An <hi>Epigram</hi> he hath to this ſence.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pro patriae in ſtrictos Codrus ruit impiger enſes:</l>
                  <l>In patriam flummas Caeſar &amp; arma tulit.</l>
                  <l>Ille ſuo patrias firmavit ſanguine leges:</l>
                  <l>At patriae peperit ſanguine Caeſar ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nemo tamen regum j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctat ſe nomine Codri:</l>
                  <l>Caeſareum nemo non ſibi nomen avet.</l>
                  <l>Quae ratio? in promptu eſt: nam qui nunc regna tuentur,</l>
                  <l>Illius oderu it iſtius acta probant.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Codrus <hi>for's Countrey ruſht on ſwords of foes:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Caeſar <hi>by fire and ſword wrought's Countrey's woes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By</hi> Codrus <hi>death his Countrey's Laws firm ſtood:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Caeſar <hi>(to rob his Countrey) ſpilt much blood.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet no King boaſteth of</hi> Codrus <hi>his Name:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But all think</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s ſtile adds to their fame.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Why ſo? the reaſon's plain: for all Kings now</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Caeſar<hi>'s acts love,</hi> Codrus <hi>his diſavow.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>What inſtruments of the Churches good our late Kings have been, old <hi>Puritans</hi> can tell: <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> (I beleeve) but claim brotherhood with old <hi>Puritans.</hi> Many a ſad heart hath been powred out by them that were really old <hi>Puritans,</hi> for the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117947:25"/> of their ſouls, and their cruel bondage under our late Kings. Mr. <hi>Prinne,</hi> I beleeve, will not refuſe the name of an old <hi>Puritan,</hi> and yet he tels us that we could have no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the laſt Kings maintaining Proteſtant Religion, which he draws as a Corollary or concluſion from all the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gagements, Oaths, Promiſes and Tyes,<note place="margin">Popiſh Royal Favourite, p. 72.</note> wherein he had tyed himſelf to the Popiſh party. From all this it is evident, that the Parliament hath not deprived the people of any thing truly a bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſing, but rather freed them from the curſe and ſnare of the reign of Hypocrites:<note place="margin">Job 34.30.</note> as the laſt perjured Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant was, and the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> little better, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand upheld <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> and publickly diſavowed him; who took the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and then refuſed to teſtifie his humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the blood that lay upon himſelf and houſe, ſhed in acting againſt the grounds &amp; ends of the <hi>Covenant;</hi> who fained ſuch a humili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion at laſt, &amp; yet is lately declared by a party in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to be walking in oppoſition to God and the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> 4ly, <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſay the people are wronged by endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of them to a war either civil or forrein. But who could have promiſed that if the King and Lords had continued we ſhould have been free from war? The Army in thei Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 16. 1648. evidence beyond all reply the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of thoſe troubles and commotions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which would have enſued upon compliance with the King, (where they alſo teſtifie their Humiliation for the Paſſages <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> urge, and I ſhould think it not very Chriſtian-like dealing to plead that as a mans teſtimony which he profeſſes his repentance of.) To what purpoſe elſe were his Commiſſions continued to the late Prince, <hi>Montroſſe</hi> and <hi>Ormona,</hi> if he kept them not as a reſerve to war upon us,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Auctá<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cum bello ſama &amp; opes. <hi>Grotius, Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt. v d. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Ant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cip. Bat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Civitas, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibilc memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, quantum brevi creverit. <hi>Saluſt. Bellum. Catilinar.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> when he had once mounted the Throne again? Beſides, a war with liberty is a far better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then quiet with ſlavery: ſo much the better, by how much a people may more eaſily reſiſt profeſſed oppoſitions, then burdens and grievances masked under the name of publick Authority, and backed with force. Our Neighbors of <hi>Holland</hi> have been ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th nking the continuing of the r war a wrong to them, that they have been great gainers by it. When the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had ſhaken off the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Kings, its a wonder to ſay (ſaith <hi>Salust</hi>) how the City grew in a ſhort
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:117947:26"/> ſpace having gotten liberty.<note place="margin">Judg. 3.27, 28.</note> 
               <hi>Ehud</hi> wronged-not <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had ſlain <hi>Egl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> he blew the Trumpet, and called the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople, by War, quite to ſhake off the Moabitiſh yoak. Would ſuch as <hi>Non-ſcibers</hi> ceaſe to abuſe the Parliaments lenity, and the Peoples credulity, we ſhould leſſe fear civil commotions: and for forraign enemies (bleſſed be God) he hath delivered us, and we hope will yet deliver. Laſtly, <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſay the people are wronged,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. P. 33.</note> becauſe the force, Bond, and ſecurity of all the Laws, are changed by this change. To this I ſay, That the Laws are the peoples Laws, they chuſe them, they make them their repreſentatives, are the ſupreme Magiſtrates, who have the ſupreme Authority, to make and confirm a Law, and as long as the people want not theſe, the ſecurity of the Laws can never fail: but their ſecurity is ſo much the more provided for, by how much any power that pretends intereſt, in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king or confirming of a Law, beſides the Repreſenters of the people is curbed. So that the Peoples Laws are more ſecure now, being out of danger of being hindred in their making by a royall <hi>adviſera,</hi> or in their execution, by protections againſt Law, flowing from an unlimited prerogative. And whereas <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſay, that the Parliament hath violated the Legal, and moſt foundational property of their Superiors; I would have them know, that the people of <hi>England</hi> repreſented in Parliament, have no ſuperiors under God, which is a truth of ſuch force, as drew from King <hi>James</hi> himſelf a confeſſion, that he was no other then the great Servant of the Common-wealth.<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. p. 34.</note> The puniſhment againſt ſuch as engage not (which <hi>Non ſcribers</hi> urge to prove, that the ſecurity of Law is looſed) is no other then the Rational practice of all our Law-Courts. <hi>viz:</hi> To deny them the benefit of the Law, who deny the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Court: And they deny the juriſdiction of all Courts which is but derivative, who deny the Supreme power of the Com-monwealth of <hi>England,</hi> which is in reſpect of other Courts, Original and fountain power.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. pag. 35, 36.</note>I have thus done with their firſt Argument, which militated ('tis <hi>Non-ſcibers paedantique</hi> word) againſt the Engagement ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractly conſidered, I ſhall come now to a view of their ſecond ground which, concerns them, (they ſay) as <hi>Engliſh</hi> men; As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſay they, are pre-ingaged, and in regard of precedent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117947:26"/> it would be perfidie (another of their Elegancies) to engage in this; Their engagements are two-fold, as Subjects, as ſworn under that relation. Their firſt argument in purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this ſecond reaſon is this. If the tye of Subjects to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates is upon us, in relation to an Authority and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which cannot be ſaid to be a Common-wealth, without a King and houſe of Lords, then we cannot engage; but ſuch a tie is upon us, <hi>Ergo.</hi> I deny the <hi>Minor,</hi> there is no ſuch tie upon them, or any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man. The power to which they ſay they were obliged, was not a power conſiſting of three coordinate eſtates, as they ſuppoſe, but, of a Polity or Common-wealth, the Univerſity of the people, being repreſented by their cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen delegates, in whom all Majeſty and ſupreme power of the Commen-wealth reſided, the King, an honorary Servant of the Common-wealth, to ſee its Laws put in execution, and the Lords, as Judges appointed to judge between the Common-wealth and King. When the Commons ſay, that the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Government conſiſts in the King,<note place="margin">Plea. page 37.</note> Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, fundamental is to be taken in its largeſt ſence, and we muſt diſtinguiſh between what is properly, what is aſcititi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly fundamental. That a people inhabiting together in one Land, be a Common-wealth having all power to themſelves, for ſelf-preſervation, and are to be governed by whom them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhall chuſe, is natural, and properly fundamental: that they ſet a King to execute their Edicts, and Lords to judge him in caſe of miſcarriage, is voluntary and improperly funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental. If therefore the Repreſentatives of the people, by the peoples fountain-power, which they neither can, or do give up to any King or Lord, do take away the King and Lords, to whom the people cannot be given up irrevocably, the King and Lords ſo taken away are no more a power, have no more Authority. Let us now hearken how they prove, that this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the King and Lords remaines, (for that the Houſe of Commons is ſtill a legal repreſentative of the people, hath been proved already: and I ſhall avoid repetitions, as far, as following <hi>Non-ſcribers,</hi> in their wild gooſe chace will give me leave.) They ſay,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. p. 38.</note> The only wayes of diſſolving Government appliable to the occaſion are, either that it muſt be done by ſome Act of thoſe in power to do it, or by forcible and violent
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117947:27"/> ejection. That what was done, was done by unjuſt violence, I deny: that it was done by them, who had lawfull power to do it, I affirm. <hi>Nonſcribers</hi> ſtrive to prove that they which did it, (for they confeſſe acts of repeal to have been made) were not qualified with power to do it, by two <hi>Medium's.</hi> 1. Becauſe they never had ſuch power committed to them, nor did any of their capaci y ever exerciſe ſuch a power. To this I confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reply, that the Repreſentatives of a Nation, (In all Nations that have had the happineſſe to enjoy ſuch) have a power to depoſe their Tyrannicall Magiſtrates, by what name or title ſoever they be called, (Proof of which may be ſeen at large in <hi>Junius Brutus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De illarum ſanctionum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, quae muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non ſunt obnoxiae, ſed in primo generis humani natu in mentes homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num inciſae ſunt, &amp; mutuo propé omnium gentium conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu comprobatae, &amp; unà cum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum natura, ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragabiles &amp; ſempiternae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennent, ipſaeque nullius imperiis obnoxia omnibus dominentur &amp; imperent. <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. Rerum. Scotic. lib. 20.</hi>
               </note> and the Author of the Treatiſe, <hi>De jure Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in ſubditos,</hi>) and that by a Law, which is of kind to thoſe ſanctions, which are not obnoxious to the changes of times, but were at the beginning of mankinde, ingraven upon the minds of men, and approved by the mutual conſent of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and (together with nature it ſelf) are irrefragable and eternall, ruling over all, ſubject to none. I borrow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of ſome honourable <hi>Scotch</hi> Lords Ambaſſadour to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in juſtification of their ejection of <hi>Mary</hi> Grandmother to our late Tyrant. And for their ignorance of any ſuch principle in Scripture, it argues their careleſſe ſearch of it. There they might find <hi>Iſrael</hi> uſing their native liberty, in depoſing <hi>Samuel,</hi> and ſetting up a King, though <hi>Samuel</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and God himſelf was intereſſed: As alſo the defection of <hi>Libnah,</hi> (one of the Prieſts Cities) from under the hand of <hi>Jeboram,</hi> becauſe he had forſaken the Lord God of his Fathers: and if one City for themſelves may reject a King, much more the repreſentatives of a whole Nation. 2. They ſay, the legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power, was ſeated in three eſtates, therefore the Abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: The falſhood of which aſſertion I have ſhewed before. Kings of politique kingdoms as (<hi>England</hi> was in <hi>Forteſcue's</hi> Judgement) cannot change the Laws,<note place="margin">2 Chronicles 21.10. Soveraign power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments. Part. page 37.</note> but the people are to be ruled by Laws only of their own making. If the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the people have by the Law of nature, a power over their Magiſtates, and have exerciſed in it almoſt all Nations, and the legiſlative power in England reſts in them, they had a power ſufficient to take away the King, and Houſe of Lords, and the powers that are taken away by their lawfull ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117947:27"/> are noe Power, nor doth any tye lie upon their <hi>quondam</hi> Subjects to obey them.</p>
            <p>What they adde <hi>ex abundanti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3. <hi>Plea, &amp;c. page</hi> 41. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7.</note> to prove the power of King and Lords ſtill to remain, is from ſuch abundance, as their ſacrifice is, whoſe voice is known by a multitude of words; indeed, meere <hi>Battology.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They ſay 1. The ſanction of that Government from God is not diſanulled, they buſie themſelves to find out a way how it may be ſaid to be diſſolved. I ſhall tell them,<note place="margin">Obedientia limitari ſemper debet, ſecundùm li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis, quam habet ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or praecipiens. Medulla Theol. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi> Theſ. <hi>54.</hi> Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> God commanding obedience to powers, commands to give every one their due; and learned <hi>Ames</hi> will tell them, that obedience ought alwayes to be limited, according to the limits of the power of the ſuperior commanding; whence he concludes that the bond of obedience to an inferiour power ceaſes, when the ſuperior power commands it not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed. We may ſafely conclude then, that the Sanction of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to King and Lords is diſanulled by the taking away of their Offices by the Repreſentatives of the People of <hi>England,</hi> their lawful Superiours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They would perſwade us that the original conſtitution of the people, in King, Lords and Commons coordinate is not made void. But the people never conſtituted ſuch a Lordly King and Kingly Lords as they dream of, they never gave them a joint power with themſelves. <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> are pittifully miſtaken, in ſaying, that the people choſe their Delegates to conſult and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currently act with the King in Parliament. They were choſen <hi>ad faciendum,</hi> as the writ of Summons ſpeakes, to make Lawes for Kings and Lords as well as others, not to be only Councellors, or concurrent actors with them. For their Reaſons (which they ſay they would produce to prove that it is unlawful for a people to depoſe their ſupreme Magiſtrate) they would be very impertinent at the preſent; for the ſupreme Magiſtrate is not depoſed as long as the Houſe of Commons ſtands, and (I doubt) unconcluſive, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they fully anſwer what Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> and Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> two of their own friends, have ſaid in aſſerting the peoples power in that particular.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Lawes (ſay they) are not repealed, that give the ſway of Government to certain perſons and their iſſue. To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that ſuch Lawes,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> (if ſuch there were) are at leſtwiſe virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally repealed in the Acts for taking away the Kingly Office and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117947:28"/> Houſe of Lords, and ſuch repeales are lawful, the whole legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power being in the Repreſentatives of the people, who (as an Houſe) are above all our common Law and poſitive Statutes, and may change, alter, and abrogate them, as they ſee moſt rationally convenient for the publick utility of the people. Theſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, engaging will appear nothing contrary to the Scriptures they quote (page 37.) The Senate was above <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives</hi> of greater power then the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and people are the higheſt power. No King is diſhonoured by a Tyrants depoſition, no Ordinance of God is violated, ſince God never ordained Tyranny in Exerciſe more then in Title. <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> are the men given to change, who joyned with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Armes againſt the King ere a while, and one of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Acts of Soveraignty is the voting and making Warre) and now are ready to joyn, with his hopeleſs brood againſt the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>44.</hi> In Judaeos &amp; Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meriſtas ſub Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantes exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceri ſolet. Grotius. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqu. Reip. Bat. c. <hi>6. Paul Servita,</hi> Hiſtory of the Inquiſition. page <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>Their ſecond Argument to prove that they are preingaged, is grounded upon their Oathes, Proteſtations, Covenants. Of which they affirm. 1. Their contrariety to the Engagement. 2. Their unremitted obligation. In the entry to the anſwer of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I cannot but obſerve, that Non-ſcribers make the ſame uſe of the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, Proteſtation and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> make of the Inquiſition-Office, which being at the firſt erected for the purging out of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Moores,</hi> profeſſed enemies to Chriſtianity, is now uſed for the keeping out of all power of Chriſtianity from coming amongſt them: ſo thoſe Oaths and Obligations which were at firſt impoſed to ſecure us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enemies of our State, and to diſcover Prieſts, Jeſuites, and Cavaliers, are now urged in the favour of a party, who hath interwoven their intereſt ſo, with that of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant <hi>Royaliſts,</hi> that (ſhould they be obſerved with <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> interpretation) our Religion and Liberties are likely utterly to be ſubverted, at leſt-wiſe we ſhould be put into as dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts for them, as we have (through Gods aſſiſtance) waded through, in our late commotions. Should we grant them that thoſe former Engagements are oppoſite to the Engagement (which well may be denied, in the proof of which negative ſome of late have worthily travelled) yet it will not thence follow, that the Engagement is unlawful, if it may be made appear that the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117947:28"/> of them is ceaſed. Non-ſcribers confeſs,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> that an Oath may be rendred void.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the revocation of a Superior, having lawful power in the matter of the Oath. The lawfulneſs of the ſuperiority of the Peoples Repreſentatives over the <hi>King, &amp;c.</hi> hath been proved, and if they had power over the Powers to whom the Oath is made, ſo that they might lawfully diveſt them of their power, they had power over allegiance, the matter of the Oath. Neither is this power of theirs over the matter of the Oaths weakened by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſay. For 1. Notwithſtanding the Oath of Supremacy, acknowledges the King to be ſupreme Governour, yet the Parliament and Kingdom are the ſupreme power, para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to him, ſaith Mr. <hi>Prinne.</hi> He was the ſupreme executioner of publick juſtice, had a ſupreme executive power, but not a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme legiſlative power,<note place="margin">Soveraign Power of Parliaments: part. <hi>1.</hi> pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>104.105.</hi>
               </note> that ſtill was retained by the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of the people. To this we may adde what Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> ſaith, that the ſupremacy given to the King, relates to the <hi>Popes</hi> and forraign Princes Authority formerly uſurped, not to Parliaments and their juriſdiction, with whom Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> well agrees, who ſcaning how the King is called ſupreme, ſaith he is called ſo in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to all forraign juriſdictions,<note place="margin">Lex. Rex. Queſt. <hi>43.</hi> page <hi>437.</hi>
               </note> and over all Perſons and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates <hi>ſeparatim,</hi> but not over Lawes, or over Eſtates taken <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctim,</hi> as convened in Parliaments. The King was <hi>Major ſingulis;</hi> but <hi>minor univerſis:</hi> ſo that aſſerting him ſupreme in the Oath of ſupremacy, infers not that his power and conſequently allegiance, was not under the power of any other: for though he was ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme in reſpect of every ſingle perſon, yet the Repreſentatives of their whole Nation were above him. 2. Notwithſtanding all the Knights and Burgeſſes of the Houſe of Commons took the Oath of Allegiance themſelves, it will not follow that they had no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over allegiance, they took that Oath as private men, not as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenters of the Majeſty of the people. As Parliament-men, they cannot fall under the notion of ſingulars, they vote not as ſingulars, but as publick Repreſentative per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as thoſe who have the power of the Counties and Towns they repreſent intruſted to them: they therefore repreſenting the community of the whole Nation are not, were not properly Subjects. Every ſingular perſon was a Subject to the King; but the whole Community or Univerſity of the Nation is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:117947:29"/> a Common-wealth, having a Nomothetique power in it ſelf, <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount</hi> to all its Magiſtrates; and this Univerſity is repreſented by the Houſe of Commons. They therefore as Repreſentatives might vote, as a Parliament might enact the abrogation of allegiance. As for that evaſion of <hi>Non-ſcribers,</hi> That the priviledge of a Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to unlooſe the Oath or Vow of his inferior is expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by the Law of God to the immediate declared diſſent of the Superior.<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. pag. <hi>53.</hi>
               </note> I anſwer, that granting this were ſo, the Parliament never gave way to the taking off the Oaths of Allegiance and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy in <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſence, they never intended to make the King above Parliaments, they never gave him an irrecoverable power, as I have ſhewed before out of Mr. <hi>Prinne.</hi> They aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Oaths ſhould be taken, whereby the King was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the ſupreme executer of the Lawes, it will not follow from hence that they made him free from all Lawes, that he ſhould not be as a Subject to them, as the meaneſt of his Subjects, as by ancient Lawes he ought to be: nay, they could not do this, it had been a giving up the power intruſted by the people to them, and could not have obliged the people,<note place="margin">Sen. Contr. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Cont. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>et ſi parendum in omnibus Patri, in eo non parendum eſt, quo efficitur nè Pater ſit,</hi> The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment gave the King a power to execute Lawes made and to be made by them the makers of all Lawes: the King by force, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to cut in ſunder the Lawes which he ought to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, and raiſes Arms againſt the Parliament his ſuperior, to the diſſolution of their Government, as they voted <hi>May</hi> 23. 1642. he hereby becomes guilty of High Treaſon, the Law excludes Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors iſſue from all hereditary ſucceſſions: here is no need of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Oathes once taken for upholding his Authority, it was forfeited by himſelf, his Superiours by Law executed him, by Law judge his poſterity uncapable of ſucceſſion, the Subjects are free from obligations, unleſs we muſt ſay, that the King is above all Lawes, as Court-Paraſites have done. <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> therefore abuſe the world, when they ſay a diſſent came too late to that which was never ſworn to by any <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> the Oaths were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver allowed to be taken, but with the neceſſary implyed <hi>Salvo,</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our obedience to the Lawes and Common wealth. Nor do they deale any better in the caſe of the Houſe of Lords. We are bound by Covenant to preſerve the priviledges of Parliament.<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. p. <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> Now (ſay they) we are confident that at the taking of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117947:29"/> and Covenant, there was no uſage of the word Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either in written Lawes, Statutes, or other Records, but what neceſſarily intended the Houſe of Lords,<note place="margin">Soveraign Power of Parliaments. part. <hi>1.</hi> p <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> as one main and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable part: but they muſt be believed upon this their confidence; for beſides confidence, (I might ſay impudence) they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to prove it. One of Mr. <hi>Prinn's</hi> Authours was as confident on the other ſide, that there were Parliaments in <hi>England,</hi> when there was neither Biſhop, Earl nor Baron: ſo that the Priviledges of Parliament may be ſafe, and yet neither Biſhop, Earl nor Baron be in any power. The Houſe of Lords were not intended as a main and inſeparable part of the Parliament, but as Judges in all plaints againſt the King and his Children; with whom, when faulty, if they collude, and neglect their truſt, the Commons might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card them; nor will it ſtand with the Rule of Chriſtian obedience, that any private perſons ſhould def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd them againſt the juſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Commons their ſuperiors, whoſe priviledges were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove theirs, and therefore are to be reſpected before them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> grant,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. pag. <hi>53.</hi>
               </note> that Oathes ceaſe to oblige by the ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the matter ſworne. The matter is ceaſed. The King and Houſe of Lords are ceaſed to be a power, in regard of right, as I have ſhewed before. Thus by their owne conceſſions, it is evident, that the former Oathes are no juſt barre to hinder them from taking the Engagement. I might adde other wayes how an Oath may be rendered unobliging: but I ſhall content my ſelfe with their owne conceſſions, and leave what they ſay in their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix, to ſuch who are engaged already, by <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling with their principles.</p>
            <p>It were but to waſte Paper,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plea, &amp;c. pag.</hi> 51. 53. 54.</note> to anſwer what elſe they ſay about the duration of the obligation of thoſe Oathes: we require no Pope nor other power to abſolve us from them: we are not drawne aſide by any changes: we ſee the powers to which the Engagements were made, taken away by their Superior power, and now being a nullity, which is in <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> language, a civil Idol, we are ſure nothing can oblige us to that which is not, either in being or right. Nor are the Powers of the King and Lords, <hi>hîc &amp; nunc,</hi> lawfull: they were lawfull heretofore, becauſe eſtabliſhed by the Legiſlative power: now the ſame power hath abrogated them, and are to us as if they had not bin. Neither is it poſſible to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117947:30"/> ſet them up again, I meane, to any meerly private. <hi>Illud poſſumus quod jure poſſumus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lucius Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> I dare not owne the poſſibility of that which is unlawfull. <hi>Brutus</hi> put his two Sons to death, for endevouring to reduce <hi>Tarquin,</hi> the reaſon was not becauſe Kingly power was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, but becauſe it was at that time unlawfull to them, the Lawes of the <hi>Roman</hi> State forbidding it. I wiſh <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſo much wiſdom and morality as that heathen Counſel had: for in all their Plea there is want of ſound reaſon to maintaine what they call the dictate of their conſcience: nor in deed bring they any thing but <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> and jingling about words to the Bar on their owne behalfe, and ſuch quirks ſhall then deſerve to be called conſcience, when ſcience falſly ſo called ſhal deſerve to be called good Divinity.</p>
            <p>If, therefore, the Power in the Engagement be neither unjuſt in its returne, or diſpoſſeſſion of others, nor preingagements hinder (which I have ſhewed) the Engagement may lawfully be taken by any <hi>Engliſhman</hi> (notwithſtanding what <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſay to the contrary) which was the thing to be demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>I have done with <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> Doctrin, and ſhould have ſpared their Application, if it had not bin as full of Calumnies, as their Doctrine of ignorance and error. Their Application is a threefold Exhortation.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>57. 58.</hi>
               </note>1. To the Impoſers of the Engagement, whom they exhort to ſtop their courſe and deſcend to reaſon it out with them, as if the ſupreme Authority of the Nation had nothing to do; but to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue with a Company of jugling <hi>Sophiſters,</hi> who muſt have ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction not ſatisfaction, and whom <hi>non perſuaſeris etſi millies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſeris:</hi> Yet I doubt not but theſe Gentlemen (which is the beſt tearm that theſe proud men can afford the <hi>Repreſenters</hi> of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the People) are able and will he willing to diſcourſe with them; but what little hopes of ſucceſs there is in ſuch a conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion, is evident from the virulency of their addreſſes here to the Impoſers of the Engagement.<note place="margin">Appendix. pag. <hi>54.</hi> Margin.</note> Theſe <hi>Baraſites</hi> (that can in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the late Tyrant quote that of <hi>Elihu, Job</hi> 34.18. Is it fit to ſay to a King, thou art wicked?) are bold to tell the Parliament, that their actions are unjuſt, ſcandalous, perjurous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There is little hope that reaſon ſhould prevail over them, who call evil good, and good evil, put light for darkneſs, and darkneſs fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> light, and ſin being condemned of themſelves. But let us hear the motions they put this exhortation on by. The impoſing of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:117947:30"/> (ſay they) is ſcandalous.<note place="margin">Dodonas Grove in Octavo page <hi>146.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Med. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> So the jingling Cavalier that calls himſelf their Majeſties Vaſſal, with the <hi>Candenians,</hi> that is, <hi>Soots</hi> riſing againſt the King, caſt a brand upon the <hi>Euſebian,</hi> the Proteſtant Profeſſion, in looſing the bands of <hi>paſſive</hi> obedience. And the Tyrant himſelf tells us, that he feared ſuch motions (as the Parliaments juſt Armes) would be an alienation of mind, and divorce of affection of his Queen from our Religion. I would know to whom the impoſing of the Engagement is ſcandalous. <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> intimate that it will be ſo to the <hi>Sticklers</hi> in the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants quarrel. And I ſay, that this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the faireſt dealing in all their Book, to acknowledge their good friends the Cavaliers, and to plead againſt offending them. But I have learned from Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> that there are two ſorts of ſcandals; <hi>ſcandala infirmorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Infiitution. cap.</hi> 12. S. 11.</note> which we muſt carefully avoid, <hi>&amp; ſcandala Phariſaeorum,</hi> this which they would make of the latter ſort, and therefore it may be ſaid of the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> and <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> their <hi>Patrons,</hi> as our Saviour ſaid of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> when the Diſciples told him that they were offended, let them alone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But <hi>Non ſcribers</hi> will prove it ſcandalous.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14.</note> How? Thus, The <hi>King</hi> laid an aſperſion upon the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that their intention was to deſtroy <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and pull down the Houſe of Lords, the <hi>Parliament</hi> abhorred the imputation, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged the contrary.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That it is no marvel, though Tyrants ſuſpect the juſt events of their Tyranny before they come upon them, and if the Parliament had profeſt againſt the Government of himſelf, his Poſterity and Court-Minions, they had done nothing ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. They ſtood too long ſhaking hands with what they ſhould have ſhaken off. Beſides, the Engagements the <hi>Parliament</hi> made in favour of him, took not away thoſe Lawes which made him and his Heires lyable to loſſe of their Crown and dignity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it could be no ſcandal to execute thoſe Lawes, or to bind the People to be faithful to them, having done what was righteous. Though <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> cannot, (yet it is poſſible to) defend againſt the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> the juſtice of our Warres, notwithſtanding the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing of <hi>Kingly</hi> Government. We entred into conteſt with them. The juſt party did maintain the liberty of the People, the unjuſt, the Tyrants exorbitancies. The juſt parties firſt deſire was to regulate thoſe exorbitancies, thinking they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from bad Councel only; but when it appeared that the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:117947:31"/> was his own worſt Councellor, and all other meanes (even af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Conqueſt of him) were ineffectual, and that by the reſtleſs machinations of the Tyrant and his <hi>Partizans,</hi> the danger was growen ſo great, that had the Tyrant remounted, an utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the peoples Liberties would have followed, it was but juſt to take away the Spring of thoſe deſtroying differences, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the Engagements made in favour of the King, being but conditionally made, that he and his Authority ſhould be preſerved, if we, our Religion, and Liberties might have been ſecured. But when theſe were like to be ruined, it was as juſt, <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> to aboliſh Kingly Government, as it was at firſt to ſeek by force to reſtrain prerogative inundations; if that therefore were not ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous in its time, neither is the impoſing of an Engagement againſt Kingly Government now ſcandalous, there is the ſame reaſon of both. It were indeed ſcandalous to our Nation, that there ſhould be found among us a prevailing party that ſhould tranſcend the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> in their falſifications and State-underminings. But (if there be any ſuch party among us) it is <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> and their party, who having ſworn the defence of the peoples liberties, would bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us one whom they would ſet in ſupreme Authority from a forraign Nation, who having ſworn to bring Delinquents to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment, maintain the unqueſtionableneſs of the Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect of our miſeries, and canonize him for a Martyr, who ſuffered for evil doing of a ſcarlettincture. And if to ſet up a Nation in a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, profeſſedly under an Authority contrary to the Authority in rightful poſſeſſion, be not the very <hi>Romaniſts</hi> State-undermining, I know not what it is; &amp; this I am ſure is <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> endeavour.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> mean, that good men in other Nations will be offended at the late actions in ours, and the preſent Engagement, conſidering former Engagements. But, I have a more charitable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of our good Neighbors, and hope that they being not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed, and conſequently free from what may divert their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from right, will juſtifie the righteous actions of our Nation, and cannot but continue in this hope, as long as I ſee other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have done the like actions, notwithſtanding the like obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to our former ones upon them.<note place="margin">Soveraign Power of Parliaments. part. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>146.</hi>
               </note> In the year 1572. <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and his Confederates in Arms proteſted againſt the Duke of <hi>Alva;</hi> yet withall, engaged themſelves to hold the Countrey of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> under the obedience of their Prince and natural Lord, as they ought to do; for ſo are the words of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117947:31"/> their proteſtation, in Mr. <hi>Prinne's</hi> Book: yet in the year 1581,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Hugo Groti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. Batavicae. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Paulus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rula, de ſtatu Reip. Bata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viae Diat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iba. Johannes de Latt. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. Belgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae. tit. Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landia. cap. <hi>7.</hi> Henricus S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus. Suecia. pag. <hi>131.</hi> &amp; Seq. &amp; pag. <hi>202. 206. 216.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> they ſolemnly abjured the King of <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine</hi> who was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Earle of <hi>Holland.</hi> And the Earles of <hi>Holland</hi> were not in any thing ſhort of a juſtly regulated King, and had as much Authority there, as the Kings of <hi>England</hi> among us, as the Authors in the Margin inform us. The States of <hi>Sweden</hi> in the year 1544, changed their Elective Kingdom into an Hereditary which they entayled upon <hi>Ericus</hi> the eldeſt Son of <hi>Guſtavus</hi> their King then, and his iſſue male, and if ſuch iſſue failed upon <hi>John</hi> the Kings ſecond Son and his heirs male, and in like manner upon <hi>Magnus,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Sudermannia</hi> the Kings younger Children, to this they ſware ſolemnly. Yet <hi>Ericus</hi> for his Tyranny was depoſed by the States, and <hi>John</hi> the ſecond Brother crowned; he dying and leaving <hi>Sigismund</hi> King of <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Oſtrogothia</hi> his 2. ſons behind him. <hi>Sigismund</hi> was crowned King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> yet becauſe he endeavoured to deſtroy the Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed among them, and Warred upon them, he was depoſed by an Act of the States Aſſembled at <hi>Stockholm,</hi> in the year 1599, and in the year 1600, both he &amp; his poſterity excluded from all government in <hi>Sweden,</hi> by a Decree of the States aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Lincop:</hi> nay more, they excluded from the Kingdom, <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Oſtrogothia,</hi> the brother of <hi>Sigismund,</hi> becauſe they feared, leſt he, out of naturall love to his brother, ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into any part or Covenant with <hi>Sigismund</hi> and his heires which might bring detriment to their countrey: and then they choſe <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Sudermannia</hi> for their King. And if the States of <hi>Holland</hi> might abjure their Earl and not be ſcandalous to us, nay, and we joyn with them, as our Nation did in Queen Elizabeth's: dayes if the States of <hi>Sweden</hi> might abjure <hi>Sigismund,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Miniſtri in hac ſententia conſtanter permanſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, poſſe, viz. Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratum ſub leges vi cogi. Buchanan. Rerum. Scot. lib. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and iſſue, and not be ſcandalous to us; nay more, and we help <hi>Guſtavus</hi> the Son of <hi>Charles,</hi> whoſe right was built upon <hi>Sigismund's</hi> ruine, I can ſee no cauſe why our actions and engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be ſcandalous to any honeſt man among them or any other Nation, that approved the equity of thoſe actions in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>Sweden. Scotland</hi> (it may be) will frowne, becauſe the current of Penſions from <hi>England</hi> is ſtopt: but they that laid the foundation of Reformation in <hi>Scotland</hi> were of another mind then their preſent Kirkmen: Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> defended the Lawfulneſs of putting Tyrants to death in a Generall Aſſembly. In the Scotch
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117947:32"/> Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Buchanan. Rerum Scot. lib. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Magis for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midamus ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miae lenita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis apud om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes bonos re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quàm apud mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s crudelitatis calumnium. Actio contra Mariam Scotorum Reginam. pag. <hi>100.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>60.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> the Miniſters were conſtant in this opinion, that the Magiſtrate, might be brought by force under the Lawes: and the Earl of <hi>Morton</hi> and other Scotch Lords Ambaſſadors to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> juſtified their depoſition of <hi>Mary,</hi> and affirmed that they might by the Law of Nature and their Countrey, have dealt more ſeverely with her, and that her life and the ſucceſſors of her Son depended upon their clemency: their Oration which was preſented to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a Latin Printed Copy where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have, ends thus, We more feare to be reprehended by good men for our over-much Lenity, then we do to be ſlandered by the bad with cruelty. Were <hi>Scotlands</hi> Kirkmen the true ſucceſſors of Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Buchanan,</hi> we could not offend them; but we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſucceſſors in the truthes they profeſſed, and the Scots Apoſtatizing, we may well caſt them in with Non-ſcribers, and contemne the offences they take againſt us, with, Let them alone, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But the impoſing of the Engagement (ſay Non-ſcribers) is ſcandalous, becauſe it takes away the Liberty of Conſcience, which the Impoſers profeſſedly maintain, and they cannot ſee any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon but that they ſhould leave Conſcience free in Civill matters, who would have it free in matters of Religion. But, beſides that the Impoſers of the Engagement, have not (for ought I know) owned the Patronage of ſo va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Libertiniſme in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as Non-ſcribers would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather upon them, their Argument may be retorted upon themſelves. It is ſcandalous, that they who hold tolleration of difference in outward formes of Diſcipline un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, ſhould claime a tolleration in Civill matters: and it would be ſcandalous in the Magiſtrate to tollerate any thing,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Feſtus Hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius. col. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Bellarmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianum.</p>
                  <p>Diſp. <hi>34.</hi> Theſ. <hi>4.5.</hi> Sam. Bolton. Arraignment of error. pag. <hi>335. 336.</hi> Plea, &amp;c. pag. <hi>61.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> or to grant any priviledge, which by the Priviledged is looked upon under the Notion of ſin; and Learned Presbyterians (into the number of whom Non-ſcribers itch to be received) rank opinions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the publike Peace with ſuch as are blaſphemous, and contrary to Fundamentall truthes, and allow the Magiſtrate an equall, nay greater Power to puniſh them that are ſeditious, then them that are ſo erroneous.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Agreement of the People, I have this only to ſay that the Parliament never owned it; and therefore Non-ſcribers do meerly Calumniate them, in laying it at their doores. But their new ſtrain of Poetry, wherein they would make <hi>Sphynx</hi> a reſolver of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117947:32"/> riddles, I muſt ſay that, for ought I have read,<note place="margin">Iſti quidem orationi Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dipos epus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectori eſt, qui Sphyngi interpres fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it. Plautus in Paenulo. Act. <hi>1.</hi> Scen. <hi>3.</hi> Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> the propoſing of riddles is onely attributed to <hi>Sphynx,</hi> the reſolution to <hi>Oedipus.</hi> And for the Riddle it ſelf, ſince Non-ſcribers are the Sphynges, I will make them (according to their own Poetry) the unriddlers. Non-ſcribers call the Government by Kings, Lords and Commons, the conſtitution of the People, yet make the People ſubject to it. So that the people (by their own conceſſions) may have a radicall virtuall Power of Soveraignty, which when they have derived, and it is in the Magiſtrate formally, they are to obey the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate made by them. The people as a Community gave their Power to their Repreſentatives, as ſingulars are required to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage. They who aggregately, as a Community are the Originall of power, may ſeverally and perſonally be the Recipients of it.</p>
            <p>The reſt of their Rhetorick is ſpent in bewayling the Tyranny,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>61. 62. 64.</hi>
               </note> oppreſſion, Injuſtice, which our Nation (as they ſay) is under, notwithſtanding the impoſers of the Engagement, profeſſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to Tyranny, and make Juſtice and Liberty their Motto. But, that you may know how good Polititians or Moraliſts they are, inſtance only (to make all theſe accuſations good) in the Act for taking the Engagement. Theſe ſervile Souls never knew what true publike Liberty is. It is an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whereby a Nation hath freedom to make and change their own Lawes, without being hindred by any ſingle mans <hi>Adviſera,</hi> or the colluſions of enſlaved Robes and <hi>Coronets:</hi> this we have: and the Non-ſcribers ſay that we want; but they want Liberty.<note place="margin">Act for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the Engagement.</note> I know none they want, but a Liberty of deſtroying themſelves and the Nation. The Act which they ſo accuſe doth Enact, that in caſe a Non-ſcriber ſue any debter, and the debter plead their not ſubſcribing the Engagement, further proceedings in the ſuit ſhall be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed: In the cloſe whereof it is provided, that no perſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of for Treaſon, Felon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, breach of the peace or good behaviour ſhall have any benefit by pleading the Plaintiffe not to have ſubſcribed: ſo that this neither amounts to Outlawry, they being under the protection of the Law, onely the payment of Debts being ſuperſeded till they ſubmit to the Supreme Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor gives the money to the Debter, but he is ſtill lyable to ſuit upon the Repentance of the Non-ſcriber, nor doth it lay them open to loſſe of Limb, Life, Eſtate or Liberty, they having Freedome to ſue any even for breach of the peace or good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117947:33"/> So that as many invectives as there are againſt the Act, ſo many falſe and wicked calumnies there are; but none v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ler then that wherein they parallell their caſe,<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> with the <hi>Jewes</hi> caſe under the feare of <hi>Haman,</hi> and intimate plots to be layd for their lives. A calumny ſo unbeſeeming Chriſtians, as it argues the Authors of it to be Acted by him who is the accuſer of the brethren, a lyar and the father of it, and upon whom as the guilt of <hi>Cain's</hi> ſin lyes (they having made themſelves guilty of their brethrens blood by juſtifying them that ſhed it) ſo <hi>Cain's</hi> curſe lies upon them alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.14.</note> they fear every one that meetes them will kill them. A calumny to be anſwered only with juſt indignation againſt and execration of their malicious jealouſie. Their hopes that deliverance would come unto them from ſome other place are in part defeated already, and he that hath delivered, doth, ye and will deliver us, from Non-ſcribers Brethren.</p>
            <p>Much may be ſaid for the Juſtice of that light puniſhment, that is enacted againſt Non-ſcribers, but more, if we look upon them as ſuch as theſe <hi>Cheſhire</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> ones would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us, that they themſelves be, <hi>viz.</hi> Such as adhered to the Parliament in the late Warres againſt the Tyrant; in ſuch refuſall of the Engagement is a ſin.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of great ingratitude, they therein denying their fidelity to them, who freed them from the yoke of Epiſcopacy, High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion-Court, Star-Chamber, (for theſe cannot be ſaid to be the Tyrants benefits, he ſtriving by his ſword to bring a greater ſlavery upon them, then he had freed them from by his word of aſſent to thoſe Bills (whoſe Authority armed them with Power to defend themſelves againſt the Tyrants Emiſſaries:<note place="margin">Superſede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> te habere ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem tanti muneris im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium aeſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem: abi i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur &amp; eſto ſervus, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam liber eſſe neſcîſti. Val. Max. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> in a word, whoſe continued labours for the recovery and continuance of their Liberties deſerve to be written with letters of gold in monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Marble, or what elſe is more durable. The <hi>Athenians</hi> had a cuſtome, that if the freed ſervant were ingratefull to his Patron, he was deprived of his Liberty. I account not thee a Citizen (ſaid the Maſter) who art an unthanfull eſteemer of ſo great a benefit; Go therefore &amp; be a ſlave, becauſe thou knoweſt not how to be free. Were Non-ſcribers deprived of their Liberty, it might be juſtified by the example of this much moralized Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's a ſin of Apoſtaſie; for what elſe, but wilful back-ſliding can it be, for them who acknowledged the ſupreme Authority of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117947:33"/> the Repreſentatives of the people in a matter of ſupreme powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Manlius e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras mihi cum praecipites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gebas Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, poſtquam mutari coepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, unus factus es ex Senonibus. Val. Max. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>3. 1</hi> Kings <hi>2.26.27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>viz</hi> the power of the ſword againſt an incroaching Tyrant, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny obligations to them, and what they repreſent, and that in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Tyrants pretended Heirs and abettors? It may be well ſaid to them as to <hi>Manlius,</hi> who after he had defended the <hi>Roman</hi> Peoples liberties againſt the <hi>Gaules,</hi> endeavoured to enſlave them, Thou waſt <hi>Manlius</hi> to me, when thou overthreweſt the <hi>Senones;</hi> ſince thou beganſt to be changed, thou art become of the <hi>Senones</hi> thy ſelf. Their lives themſelves had been forfeited in that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. They were favourably dealt with, if the <hi>Parliament</hi> only dealt with them as <hi>Solomon</hi> with <hi>Abiathar,</hi> whom he would not put to death, becauſe he had been afflicted with <hi>David</hi> in all his afflictions, yet thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt him out from the Prieſt-hood for follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Adonijah.</hi> Very little reaſon have they to complain, who find milder dealing then any of the forementioned, whoſe crimes they equall.</p>
            <p>Their ſecond exhortation is to the takers of the <hi>Engagement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>67.</hi>
               </note> whom they exhort to conſideration of what they have done, and to return back to their former ſlavery. By their fulminations, they endeavour to make the hearts of the righteous ſad,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.22.</note> whom God hath not made ſad, and to ſtrengthen the hands of the Cavaliers, that they ſhould not return from their ſlaviſh principles. To this purpoſe they uſe inducements, taken (they ſay) from the matter of engaging, wherein they charge them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With raſhneſs and precipitancy;<note place="margin">Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>68.</hi>
               </note> perhaps becauſe ſome of their flocks conſulted no more before they took the Engagement, with theſe pragmatical Confeſſors, then <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> did with the High Prieſts before they became Chriſts Diſciples. There were principles and books enough to ſatisfie Conſcience about a buſineſs of this nature, before the Engagement was thought of. Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> and Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> were ſufficient, with whom (I am ſure) ſome ſeriouſly conſulted about it, and ſome Congregations were prepared by their peaceable Miniſters to the ſubſcribing of it. For the conſtruction which <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> put upon Books writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in defence of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> it ſavours too much of that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that taught them to brag of their skill in ſoule-Phyſick. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, I ſhould think it a work as much to the ſatisfaction of Conſcience, to defend a controverted truth, as to preach the firſt principles of truth to them that never before heard them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:117947:34"/>2. <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> charge the takers of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> with ſleight grounds. I will not ſay but ſome might engage upon ſuch ſandy foundations as <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſpeak of;<note place="margin">Preface be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Kings Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture. Plea, &amp;c. page <hi>69.</hi> Canon. <hi>36.</hi> of them that were publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Anno <hi>1603.</hi>
               </note> but I dare withall confidently aver, that the moſt of ſuch are to be found in <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> Folds, whoſe Pulpit-ſtuffe, both firſt and laſt, hath been the Doctrine and perpetual infuſion of ſlavery and wretchedneſs to all their Hearers, that I may uſe the judicious cenſure of our <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conoclaſtes. Et Turpe eſt Doctori, cum culpa redarguit ipſum,</hi> it is ſuch guides ſin and ſhame, that their people in the midſt of ſuch contentions for liberty, are no more acquainted with the nature of it; which ignorance is the cauſe why ſome remain in the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal vaſſalage of a mis-informed Conſcience, and others ſin in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good things doubtfully. How their third inducement ſhould be taken from the manner and circumſtance of engaging is more then I can ſee; but <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> ſay it is ſo, in my eyes it was an Argument taken from the noxious event of engaging. <hi>Non-ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> ſay, they have heard of ſome perplext for engaging. But hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay is no ſound proof with underſtanding men; and if there be any ſuch, they ſhew more tender-heartedneſs to <hi>Non-ſcribers,</hi> whoſe ſorrow for ſubſcription when they entred into Orders, (as they call it) wherein they affirmed the Book of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> and of ordering <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> to contain nothing but what was agreeable to the word of God: few or no men, or Churches ever heard of, no not though they covenanted the extirpation of Epiſcopacy, as contrary to ſound Doctrine and the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. Furthermore,<note n="*" place="margin">Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons are as much troubled for neglecting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny voluntary ſervice of mans inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as if they had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God. Dr. <hi>Sibs,</hi> ſoules conflict. c. <hi>13.</hi> S. <hi>2.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Churches cleared. p. <hi>4.</hi> Plea, p. <hi>69. 70.</hi>
               </note> a miſinformed Conſcience may feel wrack, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony and anguiſh for that which is not really ſin. Mr. <hi>Bolton's</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canting of his opinion concerning ſeparate Churches, <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> will ſay was not ſin; yet the ſin of this ſo dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Conſcience, that he laid violent hands on himſelf; and I ſhould think Conſcience then to be in its greateſt agony, when it drives to deſperation and ſelf-murther. The terrors that fall upon an erroneus Conſcience, for ſinning againſt that error, which it is conſciencious in, is no Argument to prove that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is contrary to that error, is either ſin or falſhood.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, they addreſs themſelves to their own dear Diſciples, to whom they give Councel that might be called good, if they had not before taught them to call evil good, and good evil. Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in ignorance and error is ſo farre from being commendable, that it is a high aggravation of ſin where it is wilful. It is the cauſe, not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117947:34"/> the ſuffering that makes a <hi>Martyr.</hi> They that ſuffer as enemies to Authority, are ſo far from being followers of what is good, that they ſuffer as evil doers. But the <hi>Epiphonema</hi> of their Book, which is alſo the motive they uſe to build up their <hi>Miriones</hi> in their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, is moſt ridiculous, Be true (ſay they) to juſt principles (that is the <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> and Dr. <hi>Ferne's</hi>) and powers (that is the declared King of <hi>Scots</hi> and Pattentee-Lords) and ye ſhall not be without a King and Lord in Heaven. With ſuch ſweet alluſions do <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> feed their Sheep, and truly, were they not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like the Thiſtle-eating beaſt that made the man ſmile who never laugh't before, their lips would not endure ſuch lettuces.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.6.</note> I had rather believe <hi>Paul</hi> then all the <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and he tells me, that he that ſubmits not to preſent poſſeſſing powers, that attend on the buſineſs of ruling, receives to himſelf damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and I muſt make bold to tell <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> and their miſled followers, that if ever they come to Heaven, they ſhall find no ſuch Kings there as <hi>Non-ſcribers</hi> patronize. <hi>Tophet</hi> was of old prepared for ſuch, and Hell opens its mouth upon them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.33. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26.27.</note> as upon the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Monarch that had ſlain his people, and very few of their kind of Lords will be there. Not many Noble are called; but God hath choſen the weak things of the world to confound the things that are mighty: Unto which God I humbly bow my knees, beſeeching him who cauſeth light to ſhine out of darkneſs, to open the eyes of <hi>Non-ſcribers,</hi> and the ſeduced by them, that they together with us, may under the preſent Authority, live a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</note> And for our Nation I pray, that it may long flouriſh under that Government, which God eſtabliſhed among his own people, when he would have them beſt governed, that it may be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for its great deliverance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.5.10.</note> and walk worthy of them, that God may delight to dwell in it, be a wall of fire round about it, and the glory in the midſt of it; even ſo, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
